<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Demands to be propounded of Catholickes to the heretikes by Richard Bristow ... ; taken partly out of his late English booke of Motiues to the Catholicke faith, partely out of his printed Latin booke of the same matter.</title>
            <author>Bristow, Richard, 1538-1581.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 174 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 96 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16910</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3801.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1528</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">20191680</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 20191680</idno>
            <idno type="VID">23794</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16910)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 23794)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1706:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Demands to be propounded of Catholickes to the heretikes by Richard Bristow ... ; taken partly out of his late English booke of Motiues to the Catholicke faith, partely out of his printed Latin booke of the same matter.</title>
                  <author>Bristow, Richard, 1538-1581.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>168, [20] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>For Iohn Heigham,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l.] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1623.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Special t.p.: Certaine other demands annexed to the former. [S.l. : s.n.], 1623.</note>
                  <note>Running title: Demaundes vnto all heretickes.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-G¹² H¹⁰.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term>Heretics, Christian.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:23794:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23794:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>DEMANDS TO BE PROPOVNDED OF CATHOLICKES TO THE HERETIKES. <hi>By</hi> Richard Briſtow, <hi>Priest, and Doctour of Diuinity.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Taken partly out of his late English booke of <hi>Motiues to the Catholicke faith,</hi> partely out of his printed Latin booke of the ſame matter.</p>
                  <p>For Iohn Heigham. With permiſſion, Anno 1623.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="quotations">
                  <pb facs="tcp:23794:2"/>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Mat. 16.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Aedificabo Eccleſiam meam: &amp; portae inferi non praeualebunt aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus eam. <hi>I will build vp my Church, and hell gates shall not preuaile againſt it.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <bibl>Marc. <hi>1.3.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Caelum &amp; terra tranſibunt, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba autem mea non tranſibunt. <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth shall paſſe: but my wordes shall not paſſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Hic libellus est Catholicus, elegans, apprimè vtilis, &amp; praelo dignus.</p>
                     <bibl>Ita teſtor <hi>Gulielmus Alanus,</hi> S. Theol. Duaci Profeſſor Regius.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="demands">
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:23794:2"/>
                  <head>DEMANDES TO BE Propounded vnto all He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes.</head>
                  <p>VNDERSTANDING (gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Reader) that many are deſirous of my late booke of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues to the Catholike faith, who notwithſtandinge cannot come therby, partly becauſe there were but few printed, partely becauſe a great parte of thoſe few fell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Heretickes handes, God ſo ordaining it <hi>in teſtimonium ills,</hi> for a witneſſe vnto them: and not minded to repaire the Printe, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though of ſom deſired: I thought good, for ſome ſatisfaction of the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:23794:3"/>ſaide, and for further propagatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the truth, to the ſaluation of my deare deceaued countrimen, to ſet out this litle Pa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>flet. which albeit to ſome may for the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity ſeme but a trifle, yet whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer will voutſafe to peruſe it, shal finde it (I truſt) full of moſt iuſt &amp; weightie conſiderations to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue the Catholikes, of this time alſo, and not the Heretikes.</p>
                  <p>The maner of it I haue concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by way of Demaundes to be made by Catholickes vnto Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes, to confound therwith the obſtinate, and to conuert the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that be more tractable. And although in theſe Demandes I wil be very briefe, as only to put the learned in minde of that they haue read or may read, and to shew them how to vſe it, to profite both the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues &amp; others: yet shall I touch
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:23794:3"/>the matter in euery one of them (by the grace of God) ſufficiently for all ſortes. But if any man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire a larger declaration of them, he shall in my late booke of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues</hi> for moſt of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> find enough; and for all of them much more in my latine book (which work, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> only promiſed, he hath ſince moſt learnedly performed) of the ſame mater, and that ſomewhat of an other ſort, &amp; in another order the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I did before in English, which by theſe Demaundes may partly be coniectured. Beſeeching moſte hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly the deceuers, if they shall clearely ſee in their conſciences, that they can not replie to theſe Demaundes; that then they will for Chriſtes ſake vouchſafe to be good to their owne ſoules, and to ſpare the ſeely people.</p>
                  <div n="1" type="demand">
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:23794:4"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 1. <hi>Demaund. Touching the diſputation made at Carthage.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>FIRST then in the name of God, let it be demanded of the ſayd deceauers, or of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Heretike, and eſpecially of them that will ſeeme to be lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, whether they haue not read or heard of <hi>Collatio Carthaginenſis.</hi> The conference, or diſputation made a Carthage in Africke, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt twelue hundred years ago, betweene Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> (on the one ſide) and his fellowes the other Catholike Bishopes of that Countrey; and on the other ſide the Bishoppes of the <hi>Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſtes,</hi> who were Heretiks, like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of that Countrey. Which diſputation being then preſently taken word for word of diuers
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:23794:4"/>ſwift Notaries, was afterwarde more breifly written by <hi>S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine</hi> himſelfe, and is at this day to be ſeene in the ſeuenth Tome of his workes, in his booke called <hi>Breuiculus Callationis:</hi> An abridg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Conference.</p>
                     <p>If they knowe of the ſaid con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, let them then be asked, whether the Queſtion there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Catholickes and the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> were not the ſame that is now betweene the Catholicks and the Proteſtants with al other Heretickes of this time: to wit, <hi>VVhich of vs haue the Church of Chriſt, wherher we, or they.</hi> And becauſe theſe Hereticks call ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly for plaine Scripture, and make as though they would yeeld moſt gladly therunto: Let them ſay, whether thoſe Catholickes did not bring for their church ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:23794:5"/>many moſt plaine teſtimonies of holy Scripture: as is more or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly to be ſeene there in another booke of <hi>S. Auguſtins,</hi> named <hi>De vnitate Eccleſiae:</hi> Of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches vnitie. Whether <hi>S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine</hi> (I ſay) and thoſe other Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholickes, did not there moſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly and moſt mightily out of the Scriptures, proue a viſible Church, begining viſibly at <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> &amp; laſting viſibly not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnto their time, but alſo vnto our time, and euen ſo continually to the worlds end. And whether ſuch a Church make not as much againſt the Proteſtantes, and all other Heretickes, as againſt the <hi>Donatistes;</hi> and as much for vs that be Catholickes now, and for ſuch as shall be Catholickes at any time to the worldes, end, as for <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> and the other Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:23794:5"/>of that time: becauſe nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Proteſtantes, nor no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Heretickes, no more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Donatists,</hi> haue ſo laſted, or euer shal ſo laſte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually, nor no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther company of Chriſtians, but onely ours.</p>
                     <p>Finally, if they will ſay, that <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> and his felowes there did not, nor coulde not out of the Scripture, proue ſufficiently ſuch a Church, let them be demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded whether they dare take parte with the <hi>Donatiſtes</hi> againſt thoſe Catholickes; and whether they will, or be able to anſwere their Scriptures, for and in behalfe of thoſe Heretiks. At leaſtwiſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they talke ſo much of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and of onely Scripture; whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther they be able all the packe of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (as <hi>S. Augustine</hi> alſo there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth of the <hi>Donatiſtes</hi>) to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leage
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:23794:6"/>for their owne Church, or Churches, ſo much as one plaine text of Scripture (as he there al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leageth for our church, in maner aforeſaide, very many, and very plaine, shewing alſo there, that it cannot erre) whether they can bring vs (I ſay) in ſo weightie a matter, as wherupon dependeth al our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouerſie, any one plaine ſaying of holy Scripture, to proue that Chriſtes Church beginning viſibly at <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> shoulde ſo continue but a time, and then af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward should vtterly either pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish, or vanish away: &amp; that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hundred yeeres after, one <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> in <hi>Saxonie,</hi> or one <hi>Caluine</hi> at <hi>Geneua,</hi> or any other in any other countrey, should bring it to life, or to light againe?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="demand">
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:23794:6"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 2. <hi>Demaund. Building of the Church.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>VVHEREAS Chriſt &amp; his Chriſtians haue, beſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des Schiſmatikes and Heretikes, two other kindes of enemies, to wit, Panimes &amp; Iewes: &amp; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the auncie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t writers haue made many goodly books againſt thoſe enemies, either to confound them or to perſwade them, that Chriſt is God, as it was then, in the firſt beginning of Chriſtians, very ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for them ſo to doe: Let the learned Proteſtantes be likewiſe demaunded, whether thoſe chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian writers in thoſe books haue not made, amongſt others this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, to proue that chriſt is God: namely Saint <hi>Chryſostome,</hi> both againſt the <hi>Panimes,</hi> in his booke named, <hi>Contra Gentiles demonſtratio, quod Chriſtus ſit
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:23794:7"/>Deus:</hi> A plaine demonſtracion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Gentiles tha Chriſt is God, and alſo againſt the Iewes, in the ſecond of his fiue <hi>Orations</hi> that he made againſt them.</p>
                     <p>That <hi>Christ</hi> (I ſay) is <hi>God,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his church, although it had but a ſmall &amp; poore beinning, &amp; eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> then very many, very migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and very fierce enimies, yet could not, nor cannot euer poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly be ſuppreſſed: but contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, being in the beginning as it were but one litle ſparkle of fire, &amp; whole floudes, yea ſeas of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions being poured out vpon it; yet could it not be extinguished but contrariwiſe (I ſay) partely hath, and partly shall ſet all the world on fire, firſt or laſt bringing all to chriſt: according to chriſts owne prediction, which he alſo doth there alleage: <hi>Aedifieabe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:23794:7"/>Eccleſiam meam,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.</note> 
                        <hi>&amp; Portae inferi non praeualebu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t aduerſus eam.</hi> I will builde vp my church, and Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates shal not preuaile againſt it.</p>
                     <p>Now let it be conſidered, whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther this argumente doe holde, if it be true which they ſay, to wit, that the church of Chriſt was not inuincible, but that it hathe bene theſe many hundred yeares quite ſuppreſſed; yea &amp; in Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtomes own time no church of Chriſt at all. For they knowe, if they graunt that the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to haue bene the true church, that they muſt gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t alſo ours now to be the true church, as being all one with that. If then they will ſay, that this is not a good argument, lett the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be further demaunded, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they dare take parte alſo with the very Iewes &amp; Paynims againſte the Chriſtians, yea and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:23794:8"/>againſt the Godhead of CHRIST himſelfe; and whether they will go about, or whether they be able (which the <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Paynimes</hi> were neuer able, nor neuer shalbe able) to anſwere this argument.</p>
                     <p>And the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againe: How they can for shame ſay, theirs to be the Church of Chriſt, &amp; not rather a plaine Apoſtaſie from Chriſt, that muſt needes labour to anſwer the arguments of CHRISTIAN men, which they haue made againſt ſuch infidels, to proue that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is God. And therfore againe, whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther it be not a ſufficient Motiue for any Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man to be of our Church, which he ſo plainely ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, &amp; anon more plainly shall ſee, to ſtand vpon the very ſame argumentes againſt theſe Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes, whereupon the Diuinitie of Chriſt himſelfe doth ſtande a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:23794:8"/>the <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Painymes.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Finally let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conſider, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be not euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t by this, that when they talke ſo much of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, to bring vs thereby into enuie, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues into fauour, they do not geue wiſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to marke that they cannot be the Church of Chriſt. For Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution is not a Motiue of it ſelfe alone to beleeue any. Otherwiſe not onely one ſorte, but all ſortes should be beleeued, becauſe all are perſecuted,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iulij.</hi> 22. <hi>Stow.</hi>
                        </note> as themſelues of late did burne certaine in Smith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fielde.</p>
                     <p>But perſecution is a Motiue af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this ſorte as <hi>S. Chryſostome</hi> here doth handle it, to wit, that Chriſt muſt be beleued to be God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, according to his owne ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no perſecution coulde, or can ouerthrow his Church, which
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:23794:9"/>being once granted, that the Church of Chriſt (I ſay) alwaies ſtandeth &amp; contineweth, let the Heretickes ſay, whether they had any cauſe to riſe: and therfore if they be wiſe, let them lye down againe, &amp; returne to the Church and ſaue their ſoules.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="demand">
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 3. <hi>Demaunde. Going out.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>VVHEREAS it is manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Apoſtles actes,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Act.</hi> 2.4.5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 28. <hi>Act.</hi> 15.</note> that the Church of Chriſt, <hi>(a)</hi> began viſibly a Hieruſalem and viſibly growing on, <hi>(b)</hi> came at lengthe alſo viſibly to <hi>Rome.</hi> Whether the Proteſtantes can shew vs out of Scripture or ſtorie, that the <hi>Romanes</hi> (with whom, as it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, we agree in all pointes) who then were in the church,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:23794:9"/>
                        <hi>went againe out of the Church,</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking at any time the communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or company of other chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans then liuing, and making a new ſeueral church or companie by themſelues aſunder. So, as it is knowen themſelues haue done, being firſt of our company: and their Captaines, for the moſt parte alſo of our Mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes &amp; Fryars as <hi>Luther Oecolampadius, Hooper, Bale,</hi> with many others: and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward breaking from our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany by diſobedience, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of their ordinarie Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours: and ſo, ſeditiouſely ſetting vp theſe factions of theirs, which now we ſee. Whether alſo they can name vs any company, that euer ſince the Apoſtles time ſo did, and obſtinatelie ſtood in it, that was not Schiſmatical?</p>
                     <p>As it is plaine, that they are
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:23794:10"/>
                        <hi>Gono out,</hi> ſo it is plaine (I ſay) that we neuer went out, wherof it foloweth ſenſibly, that as they be notwithin, ſo we be ſtil within And therefore let them be vrged, what they can ſay to this, either for themſelues, or againſt vs. Or rather let them, if they be wiſe, geue ouer, and quickely without more a doe come in againe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="demand">
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 4. <hi>Demaunde. After ryſing.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>WHETHER they be able, to name any time, ſince the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles time, when our Church firſt <hi>Aroſe:</hi> Or (becauſe they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe not onely our company, as Schiſmatiks, but alſo our Faith as Heretikes, and alſo almoſt all our Religion, as plaine Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tats) whether they can name any certaine Author and firſt begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:23794:10"/>of the peculiar Articles of our Faith and Religion, but Chriſt and his Apoſtles onely? Let them be vrged to name the Article, the time, and perſon. Sure it is, that they can name no ſuch.</p>
                     <p>But on the other ſide, it is eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that their companie or companies beganne, of late; the Author therof is knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the time of his riſing not onely recorded in Hiſtories, but alſo fresh in the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders memories, and very manie Articles of his Doctrine before vnheard of. Many ſuch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panies are noted in Hiſtories, riſing ſo with new Articles, after the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining of the church as <hi>Nouatians Sabellians, Arrians, Pellagians,</hi> and very many moe. Now for defenſe of their owne doing, let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> looke amongſt them all, and name vs ſome one of them, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:23794:11"/>this <hi>their riſing afterward,</hi> was not Schiſmatical, nor their Articles Hereticall? Sure it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, that they can name no ſuch, and therefore is it euident, both that we bee ſtill the true, and Primitiue or firſt chriſtians: and alſo that they be of a new falſe makinge, and not true chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="demand">
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 5. <hi>Demaund, VVondred at.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>ALso whether at any time the chriſtian people wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at our Religion &amp; Doctrine or any point therof, as then firſt appearing, and afore not heard of: and whether the Paſtors and Doctors of the church then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently controled the ſame as new &amp; diuerrs from the Doctrine that was before? And whether that all
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:23794:11"/>Hereſies were not ſo wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred at, and ſo controlled at their firſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing? WHETHER alſo that which ſeemed ſo ſtrange to them that ſtoode in vnitie, which was ſo gaineſaid &amp; reſiſted, in bookes Diſputations and councels, by them that had the charge of the Church of Chriſt, were not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes Hereſie, &amp; the Profeſſors of it (if they were obſtinate) al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies Heretickes, without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception?</p>
                     <p>As our doctrine therfore, which euen from Chriſt &amp; his Apoſtles, is come quietlye to our handes without ſuch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tradiction, is ſure and Catholike: ſo that of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtantes and Puritanes, which was ſtreight with the ſworde of Gods Church ſticked in <hi>Luther,</hi> and neuer ſince hath ceaſſed to be by learned Catholike men con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:23794:12"/>and hath beene by a Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Councell alſo examined and accurſed,
<note place="margin">At Trent</note> nor neuer shall be able to get one day of quiet poſſeſſion, but euer oppugned and aſſaulted, vntill it be quite againe diſpat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, as all other Hereſyes haue beene before it: is moſt certainly without all doubt hereticall.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="demand">
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 6. <hi>Demaund. The nature of Catholikes.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>VVHENSOEVER there was ſuch Going out, and ſuch after riſing of ſome, &amp; ſuch won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering at it of others: whether al wayes then, in talke &amp; in books, one ſort of Chriſtians were not commonly called <hi>Catholikes,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Aug. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. ep. Fund cap.</hi> 4 <hi>&amp; de vera relig. c.</hi> 7</note> and well knowne by that name. And whether the ſaid Chriſtians were not alwayes true Catholikes; &amp; ſo at length of all men confeſſed
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:23794:12"/>to bee,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Victor deperſe-Vand. l.</hi> 3. <hi>fol.</hi> 34</note> whatſoeuer ſmoke for a while their enemis made againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by putting other names vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them?</p>
                     <p>And now at this time of their Going out, &amp; new riſing, let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſay, whoſe name that is, ours or theirs? for example: At <hi>Paris</hi> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry lately a young Gentleman of our nation, called <hi>M. Culpeper,</hi> ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on his death bedde: the night before he died, there came vnto him a countrye man of ours, as he ſaide, vpon a meſſage, And being there vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> admitted vnto him, by them that were about him pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for him &amp; teaching him how to dye; after that he had done his Maſters commendations, by &amp; by he broke out, <hi>&amp;</hi> ſaide vnto him in theſe very wordes: <hi>O Maſter Cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peper, In any caſe renounce the Catholike faith.</hi> Now, who hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:23794:13"/>this, and knoweth not, what faith that good felow meant? as himſelfe alſo would not ſo haue ſpoken, but that he knew well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, the tearme to be neither ſtrange, nor ambiguous, nor ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure? Or whether should I alſo not be vnderſtoode if I should tel further, how the Gentleman died Catholikely, notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, &amp; that a little before his death he ſaid, as in an agonie to a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like learned holy man, his leader and director in ſoule matters that ſtoode then by his bedde ſide: <hi>O tell me, I praie you, am I in the right waie?</hi> And he aſſuring him that he was: <hi>That is well,</hi> quoth, he: <hi>And will you goe with me:</hi> The ſaide catholike affirming, that hee woulde: <hi>That is well,</hi> quoth he againe: and ſo laye ſtil a while. And anon againe he ſaid
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:23794:13"/>
                        <hi>But tell me, I pray you, am I right?</hi> And he againe with good words aſſuring him: <hi>That is well,</hi> ſaith <hi>the</hi> Gentleman againe: <hi>And will you goe with me?</hi> Then after his anſwere, a litle ſilence againe: and with very cheerefull counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance the Gentlemen ſaieth: <hi>O now I ſee my ſelfe, that I am right. Beholde, my good Angell hath moſt gloriouſſye appeared vnto me, and shewed me the dore open for me, that I nay euen now enter in. But you</hi> (quoth he to the good man, with whom he talked) <hi>may not yet come.</hi> And ſo lying a while longer with a ſmilinge counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, gaue vp his happie ghoſt:
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iul.</hi> 24.</note> Dying, I ſay, a Catholique By which name here I aſke the Proteſtant, whether they know not what I meane? As likewiſe in all other bookes written now
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:23794:14"/>adaies, when they happen com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly vpon that name, whether they or any body elſe ſtagger at it as not knowing, whether we or they are meant therby?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="demand">
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 7. <hi>Demaund. The name of Heretikes.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>LIKEVVISE, whether they that haue beene of chriſtian men, at any tyme ſince hereſyes firſt roſe, commonly called He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiks, &amp; plainely known by that name, haue not alwayes been he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes alſo indeed, and ſo euer in the end,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Soz. li.</hi> 7 <hi>ca.</hi> 4. <hi>Iren. li.</hi> 3 <hi>ca.</hi> 15.</note> of al men confeſſed to be. Let them runne ouer the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall Hiſtoryes, and writings of the Fathers, and bring vs ſome exception.</p>
                     <p>And let them ſay withall, at this tyme, whoſe name that is, ours or theirs. As in bookes writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:23794:14"/>now a dayes; vpon whome that name runneth, and that ſo roundly, that the Reader (I war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant you) whoſoeuer he be, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſticketh at the matter, but knoweth well of whome he rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, to wit, of them, and not of vs.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="demand">
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 8. <hi>Demande. The Name of Protestantes.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>VVHETHER out of all this tyme ſince Chriſts Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Hier. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Lucif, Aug. de vtil. cre. c.</hi> 7. <hi>Chriſ. ho</hi> 33. <hi>in Acta. Ire. li.</hi> 1. <hi>ca.</hi> 20. <hi>Lact. li.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 30. <hi>Opt. li.</hi> 3.</note> they can bring vs any that in reſpect of the doctrine, which they did profeſſe, or in reſpect of the ſeueral company, with which they did communicate, had a new name, made of ſome mans name, or otherwiſe taken vp; whereby they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly tearmed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, and in the world generally were tearmed, and immediatly known thereby (but if they were obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate)
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:23794:15"/>they were euer Heretikes or Schiſmatikes: as <hi>Arians, Pelagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aus, Donatists, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Againe, at this tyme, which of vs haue ſuch new names, as whoſe names theſe be, <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, Puritans, Preciſians, Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpotted brethren, Fellowes of loue, Superilluminate, Porklinges, Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therans, Caluiniſtes, Anabaptiſtes,</hi> with many ſuch more? And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let them be asked, whether they can auouch their common ſlander, that among vs alſo there are ſuch names, as <hi>Dominicans, Franciſcans, Ieſuites,</hi> with ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther names of our Religious? Let them tell vs then, what ſeuerall article of fayth, or what ſeuerall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munions thoſe Religious haue: and briefly, whether it be not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident, that they, &amp; we that are not Monkes, be both of one faith,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:23794:15"/>and both of one communion, that is to ſay, both frequenting the ſame churches, and the ſame Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes. And as for the name of <hi>Papists,</hi> let them shew, that it was euer heard of before <hi>Luther.</hi> Sure it is, that it was not: &amp; therefore can it not be the name of vs, who (by their owne confeſſion) were many hundred yeares before <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> was borne; and not all that while without a name, but then, and now,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Aug. de vtil. cre. c.</hi> 17. <hi>&amp; to.</hi> 6. <hi>Ser. con. Ar. &amp; Col.</hi> 3 <hi>diei. nu.</hi> 2. <hi>Baſil. ep.</hi> 71.</note> and euer named <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes,</hi> although it pleaſed <hi>Luther</hi> to nicke-name vs Papiſts, as other Heretiks afore alſo nicke-named the true Catholikes, our fore-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, calling them <hi>Homouſians, Caeſarians,</hi> and ſuch like.</p>
                     <p>Let them tell you this alſo: why they doe not tearme vs by ſome one Popes name, as, <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorians</hi> of <hi>Gregory,</hi> or <hi>Leonians</hi> of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:23794:16"/>
                        <hi>Leo,</hi> that was when <hi>Luther</hi> began, or in like manner of ſome one or other. So as we tearme them of Luther <hi>Lutherans,</hi> of <hi>Caluin Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinists,</hi> and others, <hi>Arrians</hi> of <hi>Arius, Pelagia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> of <hi>Pelagius &amp;c.</hi> Why (I ſay) do not they likwiſe tearme vs by the name of ſome one Pope, but generally Papiſts of Pope, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as there haue bin Popes alwayes ſince the Apoſtles times? What is the cauſe of this difference in our dealing. Let them (if their wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome can) giue me any other cauſe, but only this which bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly condemneth them, and plainly cleareth vs: That, whereas we haue truely to charge them, and all other Heretickes, with fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing ſome one man, that was a new Maiſter, and a deuiſer of ſome new doctrine: they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſo charge vs with any one
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:23794:16"/>Pope at all, becauſe the Popes doctrines that we doe follow them in, were not at any tyme newly deuiſed by them, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued of the Apoſtles, &amp; ſo kept continually of them al, euen vnto this day. And therfore <hi>Luther</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing nothing to charge vs with in this foreſayd manner, inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this general tearme of Papiſts, manifeſtly againſt himſelfe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rightly ſcanned, as the wiſe doe ſee.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="demand">
                     <head>The 9. Demande. Conuerſion of Heathen Nations.</head>
                     <p>VVAEREAS Chriſt did ſay that All Nations should bee conuerted from their Paga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme, and be taught,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Io.</hi> 10 16. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28 19 <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.20.</note> and heare his Goſpell preached vnto them: and whereas his Apoſtles be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne moſt gloriouſely to doe the ſame: let the Proteſtantes be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:23794:17"/>who they are, that did, and doe accomplish the ſame?
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 20 c. 18.</note> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they euer conuerted any Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from Paganiſme to be Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and not rather doe only a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerte Chriſtians from the faith of Chriſt, ſo as all other Heretikes haue done before them? And on the other ſid, whether they know not, how euen at this preſent our church filleth very many &amp; moſt ample Nations of the Eaſt, and weaſt India with the Ghoſpel, &amp; knowledg of chriſt? And whether they do not confeſſe themſelues, that likewiſe all the other Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which haue beene conuerted within theſe 1000. years, which are very many, were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted by our Church? Then, of other na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions afore co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted, let them be vrged to name any one, either co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted by them, or not conuerted
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:23794:17"/>by vs, but by ſome other Church and to ſome other Ghoſpell, or ſome other Chriſt?</p>
                     <p>Finally let them peruſe all Hiſtories, &amp; report truely, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they do not al note, thoſe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, then to haue beene conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto chriſt, when they were conuerted vnto our Religion: &amp; if any but we chanced to haue to do with the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſion of certain, that their conuerſion was neuer accompted right and good, vntill they were amended by vs, and (namely) vnited to the Sea of <hi>Rome.</hi> And therefore let them be asked, whether we be not, or who els be chriſts witneſſes <hi>vſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ad vltimum terrae,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Act.</hi> 1.</note> euen to the furtheſt end of the earth.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="demand">
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:23794:18"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 10. <hi>Demaunde. Touching Miracles.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>VVHEREAS againe Chriſt confirmed his owne prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching to the Iewes by working of Miracles,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Io.</hi> 10.37. <hi>&amp;</hi> 12.37. <hi>&amp;.</hi> 15.24. <hi>&amp;</hi> 20 30.31. <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.17. <hi>Io.</hi> 14.12. <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.20</note> &amp; ſending his Apoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les with their Succeſſors to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert all other Nations, promiſed and fortold, that he would com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme their preaching likewiſe with Miracles, as alſo the Ghoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell ſayth that he did.</p>
                     <p>We aske the Proteſtantes, whether they know not by Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoryes, that at the conuerſion now of the Indes, and afore alſo at the conuerſion of thoſe other nations, by our church, great Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles are, and euermore were wrought by our preachers. And whether it follow not therupon, that our Preachers are they, whome Chriſt ſent out, and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:23794:18"/>with whom chriſt worketh: &amp; that their preachinge is true, as chriſtes preaching was true, and his Apoſtles preaching true, and that our Nations therfore be wel conuerted as <hi>S. Peter, S. Barnabee</hi> and <hi>S. Paule</hi> doe proue therby (I ſay, by Miracles) that the firſt Gentiles were well conuerted by them?
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Act.</hi> 11.17. <hi>&amp;</hi> 15.9.12.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>And beſides the firſt conuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Nations, whether they read not in moſt approued authors, that afterward alſo almoſt continualy in euery Nation of our church, moſt vndoubted Miracles be, and haue bene wrought, innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble holy men and women of our church approued and honored by God with that gift, as <hi>S. Bernard S. Frauncis S. Dominicke, &amp;c.</hi> and very many articles &amp; pointes of our Doctrine alſo in particuler
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:23794:19"/>ſo confimed, as <hi>the B. Sacrament,</hi> the ſigne of <hi>the Croſſe, Relikes. &amp;c.</hi> In ſo much that the auncient Chriſtians writinge againſt the Iewes and Paynimes <hi>for the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head of Chriſt,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Aug. de ciui. Dei lib.</hi> 22. <hi>ca.</hi> 5.8. <hi>&amp; de v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til. cred. c.</hi> 14.15 16. <hi>&amp; Re. lib.</hi> 1 <hi>cap.</hi> 14. <hi>Chry. to</hi> 5. <hi>cont. Gent. de vita Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bila. col.</hi> 885.</note> do firſt shew, that the miracles of Chriſt him ſelfe and his Apoſtls were wrought to ſet vp aviſible Church, that shold continue for euer (wherof it folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth, that all Heretickes do riſe in vaine:) And ſecondly they do by ſuch Miracles of the Church, as I haue ſaide daily to bee ſeene, proue vnto thoſe Infidels the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, recorded in the holy Scripture, which thoſe Infidels did denie, becauſe they did not ſee the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.) Let the Proteſtantes therfore be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, whether they dare ioine here in alſo with the Infidels againſt the chriſtians, and anſwere for
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:23794:19"/>them, that the argument is not good, becauſe theſe Miracles of <hi>the Croſſe,</hi> and of <hi>Relickes,</hi> and ſuch like are not Miracles, but illuſions. And then whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they shal by and by heare the Infidels ſay euen ſo alſo of Chriſtes &amp; his Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſtles Miracles, let vs ſee a Gods name, how wiſely the Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts wil replie, &amp; shew them a plaine difference betweene chriſtes Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, and our Miracles? Or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther shal we not ſee them hereby not only confirme the Infidels in their incredulitie, but alſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare weake chriſtians to infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, yea &amp; them ſelues alſo rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to geue ouer therunto: as in our countrey (God helpe) who ſeeth not?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="demand">
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:23794:20"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 11. <hi>Demaund. Touching England our own Countrye.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>AND here namely of our own Countrey a few queſtions: whether it be not plaine by the Hiſtorie of Venerable <hi>Bede</hi> our Countreiman, and other Authors that our English Nation a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years agoe, in <hi>S. Gregories</hi> time, was conuerted
<note n="a" place="margin">
                           <hi>lib. ca</hi> 23.</note> by men of our catholike <hi>Romane</hi> church? and conuerted to al points of our catholike <hi>Romane</hi> Faith, as
<note n="b" place="margin">
                           <hi>lib.</hi> 1 <hi>ca.</hi> 26</note> 
                        <hi>Maſſe,</hi>
                        <note n="c" place="margin">
                           <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>k.</hi> 14.24</note> 
                        <hi>Purgatorie,</hi>
                        <note n="d" place="margin">
                           <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 32</note> 
                        <hi>Saints, &amp;c.</hi> And, that our ſaide conuerſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was confirmed then
<note n="e" place="margin">
                           <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>ca.</hi> 26. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>ca.</hi> 2. <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>ca.</hi> 13 f. <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>ca.</hi> 4</note> by wonderful Miracles.</p>
                     <p>And if this be not enough, wheras the <hi>Britons</hi> or welsh men were conuerted before vs more then foure hundred years, aboue fourtene hundred yeares agoe, in
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:23794:20"/>
                        <hi>S. Eleutherius time:</hi> whether they were conuerted by <hi>S. Eleu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therius</hi> to one faith? and we Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish men by <hi>S. Gregorie</hi> to
<note n="a" place="margin">
                           <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 7.8.15.18</note> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther faith? Or, whether
<note n="g" place="margin">
                           <hi>lib.</hi> 2 <hi>ca.</hi> 2</note> the greateſt point, wherein the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes of <hi>VVales</hi> differed from our A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, were not <hi>about the Son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day vpon which</hi> Eaſter should be kept, which the Proteſtantes pardy (although ignorantly, and falſely) make to be no great matter. And, whether in that point alſo, and in any other of leſſ waight, wherein they did differ, the truth were not (euen by the Proteſtantes owne confeſſion) on our Apoſtles ſide, &amp; not vpon the <hi>welshe</hi> mens ſide.</p>
                     <p>Now for them to departe from this faith ſo longe continuing, ſo confirmed, ſo auncient, ſo cloſe to the Apoſtles time, &amp; therfore (as
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:23794:21"/>alſo becauſe it came from <hi>Rome</hi>) ſenſibly Apoſtlicall? hauing alſo the plaine deuine teſtimonie of ſo many Scriptures,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſ.</hi> 71. <hi>b.</hi> 10. <hi>&amp;</hi> 96. <hi>a</hi> 1. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41. <hi>a</hi> 1.5. <hi>a</hi> 2. <hi>a</hi> 4.49. <hi>a</hi> 1.60. 5. <hi>b.</hi> 9. <hi>Soph.</hi> 2. <hi>a</hi> 11.</note> as amongſt the conuerſion of Nations ſpeake ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly of Ilandes: let them ſay, what moued them? what Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles did <hi>Luther</hi> worke? what Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles did <hi>Caluine</hi> worke, or any other of their new maſters, and falſe Apoſtles? yea what other thinge caried away our contrey into this Apoſtaſie, but only ſinne, as all the world knoweth? &amp; the ſame alſo daily ſo filling it with all kinde of ſinne and wickednes, that there muſt needs follow of it, deſtruction both temporall and eternal?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="12" type="demand">
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:23794:21"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 12. <hi>Demaunde. Viſions.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>VVhether they knowe not that both in
<note n="a" place="margin">
                           <hi>Bed. Hist. l.</hi> 2 <hi>a</hi> 6.12</note> our Country and alſo in al other Chriſtian na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, innumerable holy Perſons of our communion, &amp; very many points of our doctrine, haue been by God from heauen approued with moſt vndoubted viſions, &amp; them alſo very often ſenſible: as for example. The
<note n="b" place="margin">
                           <hi>Amb. ſerm.</hi> 61. <hi>Aug. de vnit. Ec. cap.</hi> 26. <hi>Paulin. ep.</hi> 12. <hi>ad Seue c. Io.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 33. <hi>Act.</hi> 2. <hi>c</hi> 17 <hi>&amp;</hi> 22 <hi>b</hi> 6. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. <hi>a</hi> 1.</note> Relikes of <hi>S. Geruaſius,</hi> and <hi>Protaſius</hi> reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led at Milane to <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; with infinite moe of like ſort? And whether it be not eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent (c) in the Scriptures, that God vſed the ſame meanes to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend vnto vs Chriſt himſelfe, &amp; his Apoſtles, and their doctrine? And therefore whether it be not likewiſe euident, that whiles they ſcoffe at al viſions, they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:23794:22"/>the world heereby alſo to ſcoffe at Chriſt himſelfe.</p>
                     <p>Finally aske them, why, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are diſpoſed to ſcoffe at viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, they go to certaine obſcure writinges, and picke out of them that ſeemeth for their purpoſe? Why are they afrayd to doe ſo with the foreſayd viſions of S. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> and innumerable other ſuch like, moſt famous, and moſt certaine, which make no leſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, and no leſſe for vs, then thoſe others that they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coumpt to be vncertaine.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="13" type="demand">
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 13. <hi>Demaund. Honour of Croſſes.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>VVHETHER they haue not read in auncient Chriſtian Bookes made againſt the <hi>Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimes,</hi> alſo this argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, to proue that Chriſt is God: becauſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:23794:22"/>a Galous tree, and euery other inſtrument of execution, be accompted a vile and vnhonou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable thing;
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Deut.</hi> 21 <hi>d.</hi> 23. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. <hi>b.</hi> 13.</note> &amp; of al a croſſe was accompted moſt vile, &amp; moſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed: yet Chriſt hath ſet his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Croſſe in ſuch high honour, &amp; eſtimation, that Emperours and Empereſſes, Kings, &amp; Queenes, and all other, men &amp; wemen, do not only thinke themſelues hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, if they can get neuer ſo litle a piece of it, putting it moſt hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably in ſiluer and gould, and ſo hanging it about their neckes; but alſo make very great accompt of the only ſignes thereof, ſetting it euen in their Regall crownes, and dayly printing it in the moſt noble and moſt notable part of their bodyes, euen in their fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heades. In ſo much that S. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſostome</hi> ſayth boldly thereupon:
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:23794:23"/>
                        <hi>Vellem audire à Pagano &amp;c.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Chryſ. to.</hi> 5. <hi>con. Gent. quod Chriſtus ſit Deus. col.</hi> 1033</note> 
                        <hi>I would fayne learne of a Paynim, how it is that the Signe of ſo curſed a death is ſo much deſired of all men, but only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe great is the power of him that was crucifyed?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Aske the vnſigned Heretickes, what they can anſwere here for the vnſigned Panym? yea whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be not ashamed &amp; wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of that Religion, that ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded without pertaking with the <hi>Paynims</hi> againſt the <hi>Christians,</hi> nor without anſwering the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Chriſts owne Diuinity: which yet they are not able to doe? And let Chriſtian people remember, that Chriſtians haue euer vſed to croſſe themſelues; &amp; that therfore theſe vncroſſed Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teſtants, vnlike and repugnant to Chriſtian men of all tymes, ſtand poſt alone. And then let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:23794:23"/>conſider, whither ſo deſerte away is like to cary them, if they returne not the ſoner to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Chriſtian way.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="14" type="demand">
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 14. <hi>Demande. Vertue of Croſſes.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>AGAIN, whether they haue not read in ſuch Bokes,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Chryſ. ibidem. Euſ. de laud. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                              <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant. pa.</hi> 365. 266 367. <hi>Lact. l.</hi> 4 <hi>cap.</hi> 27.</note> not onely (as I haue now ſaide) the Honour of the holy Croſſe, &amp; the very Signes of it, but alſo, and much more, the wonderful pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and miraculous vertue of the ſame, both (I ſay) of Chriſts moſt holy Croſſe, and alſo of the very Signes thereof, taken and vſed in argument, to proue vnto the Painyms, <hi>that Chriſt is God?</hi> As, bycauſe the ſame driueth awaie Diuells out of Idolles, and out of mens bodies, and healeth all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes, &amp; raiſeth alſo many times
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:23794:24"/>the very dead them ſelues. Lett them shew the Painims the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> how this argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t alſo may be anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, if they can. Or rather let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> forſake that Religion, that ſo ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth with the Paynims againſt Chriſt? and returne to Chriſtian men &amp; ſtand with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for Chriſt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="15" type="demand">
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 15. <hi>Demaund. Honor of Saintes.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>VVETHER they read not like wiſe in ſuch bookes,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Chriſ. ibidem. Aug. ep.</hi> 42. <hi>&amp; in Pſa.</hi> 44. <hi>Theod. de Cur. Grac. af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. l.</hi> 8.</note> alſo this argument to proue vnto the Paynimes, <hi>that Christ is God:</hi> Becauſe he hath ſet his holy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes in ſo highe honour, that the very higheſt, as Kinges and Emperours, &amp; al others doe pray vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and runn to their very Graues and Relikes, and, thinke them ſelues happie, if when they be dead,
<note n="a" place="margin">
                           <hi>chriſ. ibi. Col.</hi> 1033</note> they may be buried,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:23794:24"/>not onely by their Bodies, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo nighe to their Chapelles. Lett them therfore here againe helpe the Painims, if they can. Or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let all true Chriſtians looke to them ſelues, and defie both the Painims, and them.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="17" type="demand">
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 17. <hi>Demaund.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Chriſ. to</hi> 5. <hi>cont. Gent. de vica S. Babyla. Theod. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> ibidem Aug. d. Ciu. l</hi> 22 <hi>cap.</hi> 9.</note> 
                        <hi>Vertue of Saintes</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>AGAIN, whether they read not in ſuch Books, not only (as I haue now ſaide) the Honor of Saintes, and of their Relikes, but alſo, and much more, the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous power of both, of Saints (I ſay) and of their very Relikes: vſed in argument, to proue vnto the Painimes, <hi>that Chriſt is God</hi> As, becauſe they deſtroy Idolles, that is to ſay, the very Godes of Painims, they yet being but the Seruants of Chriſt our God? and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:23794:25"/>becauſe they expell Diuells alſo out of mens bodies, and heale all diſeaſes, and raiſe many times the dead? and alſo mightely and very beneficially doe amend cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt maners of men, and inflame them with deuotion towardes God? Let the Proteſtantes here once againe help the Painims, if they can. Or rather let them at lenght leaue that Religion, by which they haue ſo filled our cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trey with Painims and Atheiſtes bycauſe (as all men may ſee) it ſtandeth ſo ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly againſt ſo many moſt certain groundes and argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Chriſts owne Diuinity.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="17" type="demand">
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 17. <hi>Demaund. Exorciſing of Diuels.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>YET once againe: whether they read not in ſuch Bookes alſo this motiue propou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:23794:25"/>to the
<note n="a" place="margin">
                           <hi>Luc.</hi> 9.1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10. <hi>c.</hi> 19. <hi>&amp;</hi> 11. <hi>c.</hi> 20 <hi>Mar.</hi> 16. <hi>d.</hi> 17.</note> Goſpel) by moſt au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Chriſtian
<note n="b" place="margin">
                           <hi>Iustin. con. Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon. Tertul. in Apol. &amp; ad Scapula<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Cip. adu. Demetr. &amp; de va nitate I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolorum. Arnob. contra Gentes Lact. l.</hi> 2 <hi>cap.</hi> 16.</note> writers to the Painimes: That their Idolles were not Godes, but that <hi>Chriſt is God;</hi> becauſe Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men haue amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt them an ordinarie pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; giuen by Chriſt, to adiure Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelles, yea and the ſame Diuelles that were the Painimes Goddes: &amp; with meruailous authoritie to encreaſe vpon them infinite tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, vntil by ſuch conſtraint, they both confeſſe their names, with other thinges that they be asked, and alſo finally depart out of the bodies which they had po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed. The practiſe wherof any man that liſt, may ſee alſo at this day in our Church: as my ſelfe, and many other of our Countrei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men haue ſeene, and in all ages the like practiſe of our Church, (as the learned Proteſtantes doe
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:23794:26"/>know) is recorded in Hiſtories: as the Diuell neuer ceaſſeth thus vexing of men, ſo the church ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ceaſing to vſe this power of hers againſt him for ſuch as ſeeke vnto her.</p>
                     <p>Now let the Proteſtants that reſiſt this church be asked, what they can anſwere to this Motiue, in behalfe of the Painimes, and of the Diuels themſelues, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they dare ſay, or can shewe, that the argument prooueth not the Idolles vanitie, and chriſts Diuinitie?
<note place="margin">S. <hi>Cyp. de vanitat. Idolor. num.</hi> 4. <hi>Con. Car</hi> 4. <hi>ca.</hi> 7. <hi>Paulin. in Nata</hi> 4. <hi>S. Fe licis.</hi>
                        </note> Or that in olde time it did, but now doth not? And what difference they can geue vs betwene the churchs Exorciſmes then, and now? Or rather let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> humblie confeſſe their faulte, that in drawing men away from this church, they haue drawen them from their vndoubted ſaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:23794:26"/>and ſo lefte them deſolate and open to the Diuells inuaſion, working therby for the Diuells kingdome ſo manifeſtly, that his raigning in their countreis, peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and proper perſons is moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident and notorious: which our Exorciſtes would (if they might be ſuffered) geue them to ſee in many of themſelues no leſſe, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to <hi>Demetrian</hi> the Proconſull of <hi>Afrike</hi> (who yet thought himſelfe for witt &amp; tongue, againſt chriſt in defence of his Diuells, a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing <hi>orator</hi>) to whom it were good for the new preachers to conſider deeply what <hi>S. Cyprian</hi> writeth: O (ſayth he) <hi>that thou wouldest heare,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Cyp. ad Demet. num.</hi> 6.</note> 
                        <hi>and ſee them, when of vs they be adiured, and tormented with ſpirituall whippes, and by torments of wordes, caſt out of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies by them poſſeſſed, &amp;c. Vent
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:23794:27"/>&amp; cognoſce vera eſſe quae dicimus. Come and ſee by experience, that we ſay true. &amp;c. Aut ſi volueris &amp; tibi credere; de te ipſo loquetur, audiente te, qui nunc tuum pectus obſedit. Or if thou wilt beleeue thy ſelfe alſo; out of thy ſelfe shall he ſpeake, in thine owne hearing, that hath now poſſeſſed thy hart.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="18" type="demand">
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 18. <hi>Demaund. Destroying of Idolatry.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>VVHETHER they ſee not by this that I haue ſaide, that as it is our church, which hath conuerted, and doth conuert all Nations vnto chriſt, ſo it is our church, that hath deſtroied, and doth deſtroy Idolatry?</p>
                     <p>Or let them ſay, whether that both our Nation, &amp; all other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions now of chriſtendome, were not before their chriſtening, wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>shipers
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:23794:27"/>of Idoles, as <hi>Iupiter, Mars Venus, &amp;c.</hi> And whether that vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Chriſtening by vs, they haue not bene ſo fully turned fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe Idolls, that the Multitude hath forgotten their very names alſo? And therefore, whether it be any other church but ours,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Zac.</hi> 13. <hi>a</hi> 1.</note> that fullfilleth the Scriptures, which foretold of the deſtroying &amp; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting of Idolles, ouer all the world?
<note place="margin">C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                              <desc>••••</desc>
                           </gap> S. Babil.</note> And whether auncient ſtoryes and other writers doe not reporte, the ſame oftentymes to haue beene done by our holy I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, ſignes of the Croſſe, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes of Saints, and moſt bleſſed Sacramente of the Altar? And therefore againe, whether Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants in calling moſt blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly theſe points of our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, Idolatry, which (I ſay) haue deſtroyed, and doe deſtroy
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:23794:28"/>Idoles be not as blind as he that ſayth,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 20.</note> white is blacke; or rather as peruerſe, as he that ſayth; <hi>God is bad?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="19" type="demand">
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 19. <hi>Demand. Kinges.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>VVHERAS the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſpeaketh much of the conuerſion of
<note n="a" place="margin">
                           <hi>Iſ.</hi> 49.</note> Kings at length &amp; namely of the
<note n="b" place="margin">7. <hi>f.</hi> 23 b <hi>Iſ.</hi> 60. <hi>c.</hi> 14. <hi>b</hi> 11.</note> Roman Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, though firſt moſt cruell perſecutors of the Chriſtians: ask the Proteſtantes, firſt whether this doe not argue cleane againſt them, that whereas they ſay the Church and fayth of Chriſt did ſoone begin to perish and vanish quite away, that cleane contrary to them (I ſay) euen then, to wit certaine hundred yeares after the beginning it increaſed much, and florished a great deale more, catching then hold alſo of thoſe mighty Powers, before, her per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutours &amp; by their help, in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:23794:28"/>short tyme, deſtroying Idols, and building Churches; &amp; ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it ſelfe ouer all the world?</p>
                     <p>Secondly aske them, whether any one of thoſe Emperors were conuerted to their Religion: or whether ſuch of them as were to be commended (for ſome, &amp; they well known, fell afterward to be Heretikes, though not Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants.) But of them, I ſay, that were moſt Chriſtian &amp; catholik, as <hi>Conſtant. Theod. &amp;c.</hi> Aske the Proteſtants whether they are not plainely reported to haue been of our Religion, as
<note n="c" place="margin">
                           <hi>Aug. ep.</hi> 42. <hi>Euſ. de vit Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant. l.</hi> 3 <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 58.71.</note> running to Relikes, praying to Saintes, praying for the dead
<note n="d" place="margin">
                           <hi>The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> hiſt. l. c.</hi> 17.</note> ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting themſelues to the Church, and generally in all other pointes ſo to be gathered by their lawes, and ſpecially by the tyme when they liued, which tyme the here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:23794:29"/>do ſo plainely ſee to haue beene ours, that they are fayn to ſay, that Chriſts church did faile before that tyme. Thirdly wee aske them els, whether they will (for tryal of the truth) get vs leaue to appeare with them before the Queens highnes, &amp; both of vs to ioyne, with her Maieſty, in that Religion, which shalbe clearely proued to haue beene the religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thoſe Emperours: not only of ſo many Kinges and Queenes at home her noble Progenitors, but of thoſe very Emperours: (I ſay) whoſe Religion and conuerſion was ſo long
<note n="c" place="margin">
                           <hi>Iſa</hi> 60. <hi>c.</hi> 14. d 11.</note> afore more plainly foretold &amp; promiſed in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: and there, moſt ſpecially the Religion euen of thoſe, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the great Oratour of <hi>VVoodstocke</hi> namely commended of late vnto her Highnes, to wit (a) <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:23794:29"/>Valentinianus,</hi>
                        <note n="d" place="margin">
                           <hi>Theod lib.</hi> 5. <hi>c</hi> 36. <hi>Soc. l.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 21.46 <hi>Soz. l.</hi> 9. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.2.</note> and <hi>Pulcheria</hi> the Virgin and Empereſſe?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="20" type="demand">
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 20. <hi>Demaunde. In all perſecutions.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>BEcauſe the Romane Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours firſt were perſecutours &amp; Proteſtantes haue talked much of perſecution, as though we vſed them ſo as thoſe Tyrants vſed the firſt Chriſtians: to the end that the truth many be plainly know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, aske them, whether they wil be content to trye this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy of Religion which is between vs,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Comfort ſor Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiks in England. Euſ. hiſt. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 14 <hi>l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 4.9.35. <hi>l.</hi> 8 <hi>cap.</hi> 2.17. <hi>Cyp. ep</hi> 5 34.37.57.69.</note> by the religion of thoſe ancient Martyrs, and others then in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, as S. <hi>Ireneus, S. Cyprian, S. Laurence,</hi> and ſuch others as we read of in the Eccleſiaſticall Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories, where they write of thoſe perſecutions, and was ſenſibly the true Religion of Chriſt? and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:23794:30"/>yet, I warrant you, the learned Proteſtants, that haue read and ſeene all, will neuer be content to be tryed by it. They know to well, that it was not theirs. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe aske them, what it mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, that they and we be ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary in ſetting out the liues of Martyrs: their <hi>Foxe</hi> (for example) being moſt occupyed about their new fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Martyrs of this our age: and our <hi>Surius</hi> (beſides many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) being altogether occupyed about the liues of old Saintes, ſuch as haue bene euen from the Churches beginning? read their liues, and you will not meruaile, neither at <hi>Foxe</hi> on the one ſide, nor at <hi>Surius</hi> on the other ſide.</p>
                     <p>And not only in the ſundry per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions of the heathen: but aske them likewiſe of the ſundry per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions of diuers Heretikes;
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:23794:30"/>as in the perſecution of the <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> in Afrike, a little after S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustines</hi> death, whether the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiks whom thoſe Heretiks did perſecute, were not of the ſame religion, as we whome theſe he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes doe perſecute (S. <hi>Victor</hi> who then liued with them) writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that the Arrian King <hi>Hune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricus</hi> permitted the Catholiks
<note n="a" place="margin">
                           <hi>Vict. de perſe. vand. l.</hi> 2. <hi>fol.</hi> 12.</note> 
                        <hi>Miſsas agere, to ſay Maſſe</hi> in certaine Churches; &amp; afterward charged them
<note n="b" place="margin">
                           <hi>f.</hi> 19.</note> 
                        <hi>contra interdictum Miſſas e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſſe, to haue ſayd Maſſe in other Churches that they were forbidden:</hi> writing alſo, that afore him the Arian King <hi>Genſericus</hi> did forbid them all churches (<hi>Neque</hi>
                        <note n="c" place="margin">
                           <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>fol.</hi> 3.</note> 
                        <hi>vſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam orandi aut immolandi concede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batur locus. Neither any place was permitted vs to pray or to Sacrifice:</hi> And that thereupon <hi>caeperunt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotes, qualiter poterant, &amp; vbi
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:23794:31"/>poterant ablatis Eccleſijs, Diuina Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steria celebrare, The Priestes began when their Churches were taken from them, to celebrate the Diuine Miste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes, as they might, and where they could:</hi> ſo as they are fayne to doe now alſo in England: <hi>Saint Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> himſelfe being to thoſe Prieſts
<note n="d" place="margin">
                           <hi>fol.</hi> 2.</note> fellow both in perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution and alſo in Religion.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="21" type="demand">
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 21. <hi>Demaunde. Churches.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>VVHether they will be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to be tryed by the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hion of thoſe firſt chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, or temples, and chappels
<note n="a" place="margin">
                           <hi>Euſ. hiſt. l.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 24. <hi>l.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi>
                        </note> that in the foreſayd perſecutions were by the pagane Emperours ouerthrown? Or
<note n="b" place="margin">
                           <hi>Euſ. l.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 28</note> by thoſe chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, that were afterward by the Emperours, ſpecially when they
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:23794:31"/>were conuerted, built vp againe?
<note place="margin">9. <hi>c.</hi> 8.9. <hi>l.</hi> 10. <hi>c.</hi> 2.3.4 <hi>&amp; de vit Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>st. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 40. <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 41.58. <hi>Bed. hiſt. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 12.18. c <hi>Bed. l.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. <hi>Chryſ. to</hi> 5. <hi>con. ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                              <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quod Christus ſit Deus. col.</hi> 1036</note> Or by the Churches that are now ouer al Chriſtendome to be ſeene being the moſt liuely, and moſt principall Monumentes of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianitie?</p>
                     <p>And whereas the Churches now beare plaine witneſſe to our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, both in their fashion, &amp; in their furniture, as that they be bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ilded at length into the Eaſt, and the chiefeſt alſo in the forme of a Croſſe; &amp; furnished with Chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells, Altares, Croſſes, and other Images, with holy Relikes with Chalices, and other holy veſſells, and with Holy Veſtimentes, &amp;c. Aske the Proteſtants, what they reade of the auncie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; firſt Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, whether they alſo were not ſo builded, and ſo furnished? yea whether very many of theſe that are now to be ſeene, are not of the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:23794:32"/>very firſt and moſt auncient. Or when the Churches beganne to be chaunged and altered from the firſt, to a cleane contrary forme &amp; furniture?</p>
                     <p>As for example in our owne Countrey, whether of late yeares they were changed from
<note n="c" place="margin">
                           <hi>Bed. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 3.14.16. <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 2.7.</note> thoſe of our firſt conuerſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Or whether thoſe of our firſt conuerſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer from
<note n="d" place="margin">
                           <hi>Bed. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 6.8.26. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 5.</note> the former of the <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons</hi> or <hi>welshemen?</hi> Or, whether of both, Englishe (I ſay and Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tannes) there are not yet ſome to be ſeene: and they, and others as well in that Iland, as in all the reſte of Chriſtendome, ſo like and vniforme, that neither the Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes can pointe out ſo much as one that was of their Religion, &amp; the Catholickes may ſee
<note n="g" place="margin">
                           <hi>Aug. ep.</hi> 118. <hi>&amp; de bap l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 24</note> by theire vniformitie, I ſay) that they haue bene, and be al of the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:23794:32"/>Apoſtles Religion and tradition. And therefore put the Heretickes in mind of their hainous Sacrilege, partely in pulling downe ſo many of the Churches, partely in vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the reſte, and the Liuinges of al, being the poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of Chriſt and Dowries of his onely Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church, and no one of them all builded by Proteſtantes, nor for Proteſtants, nor for their we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and children.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="22" type="demand">
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 22. <hi>Demaund. Seruice.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>VVHETHER they wilbe tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the praiers that were ſaide, or Seruice that was done in the foreſaid Churches, either before they were throwe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> downe by the Tirantes, or after they wer reedified by the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, or any time ſince then?</p>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:23794:33"/>
                     <p> Let them ſay, what they reade therof likewiſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in all Antiquitie, whether they reade not expreſly that alwaies there was in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <note n="a" place="margin">
                           <hi>Cyp. ep.</hi> 69. <hi>Euſ. de vita Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                              <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 56.71 <hi>Aug. de cura pro mort. in fine.</hi>
                        </note> Praying for the dead, and Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnto Saintes; and in admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, thoſe very
<note n="b" place="margin">
                           <hi>Auguſt con. Iul. l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 8. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>de nup. c.</hi> 17 18.19.</note> Ceremonies which we now vſe, &amp; which they haue laide awaie, as Exorciſme, Exufflatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Inunction, Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Fonte with crosſinge of the water, &amp;c? And, whether they read at any time, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Maſſe did firſt come into the Churches: ye whether they find not expreſly as alwayes Altares, chalices, and Prieſtes, ſo alwaies Maſſe and Sacrifice,
<note n="c" place="margin">
                           <hi>Cyp. ep</hi> 66. <hi>August. Confeſſ. l.</hi> 9. <hi>c.</hi> 12 14.</note> euen for the dead al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, which they moſt abhorre; with the wholle ſubſtance of the moſt holy <hi>Canon</hi> which they haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed to lay away, not conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:23794:33"/>that euidentlye it came of the Apoſtles, no Heretike being able to bring forth any other origen of any peice of the ſaide ſubſtance thereof? Finally, whether in all the Maſſe or other Seruice of our Church (the which Catholickes moſt worthily doe admire) they finde any piece (although it were afterward brought in) contrarie to the olde faith, &amp; therfore what cauſe they haue to find fault with that, more then with <hi>Gloria Patri, Te Deum, Quicumque vult, Gloria in excelſis</hi> and very many more ſuch, afterward (I ſay) brought in and yet retained now by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues alſo? being all nothing els but godly exerciſes &amp; daily prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinges of the Faith, that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles taught, Heretikes impug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, &amp; the Church hath alwaies kept?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="23" type="demand">
                     <pb n="66" facs="tcp:23794:34"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 23. <hi>Demaund. Apes.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>WHETHER they haue in their Seruice, or any wher els, any thing to be commended, but they haue, like Apes, taken it of vs by imitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: as may bee ſeene in their Communion booke comparing it with our Maſſe book: in their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Courtes, Viſitations, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocations, Councels, Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nications, Burning of Heretikes, Depriuations, Degradations, &amp;c. Aud therfore aske them, how that can be the true Church, which ſo muſt, and ſo doth imitate; or that the falſe Church which ſo is imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated, and ſo worthy to be imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="24" type="demand">
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:23794:34"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 24. <hi>Demand. Prieſthood.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>ALSO whether they be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to trie Religion by the Prieſthood, that not onely theſe later hundreds of yeares, but alſo from the beginning, hath ſerued in the foreſaide churches of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome? As, whether <hi>S. Hierome S. Augustine, S. Cyprian, S. Ireneus</hi> or any other, were made Bishop or Prieſte by a King or Queene, and not by Bishops and Prieſtes; Or, whether it be not expreſſely written in many
<note n="a" place="margin">
                           <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. <hi>d</hi> 14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5. <hi>d</hi> 22 <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. <hi>b</hi> 5</note> places of the new Teſtament, that Bishops and Prieſtes should be, and alſo were made by Bishops and Prieſtes?</p>
                     <p>And as the moſt au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cient prieſts of Chriſtendome were made by ſuch, ſo againe, whether they were not made
<note n="b" place="margin">
                           <hi>Hie. l.</hi> 14. <hi>in Ezec.</hi> 45 <hi>Paulin. ep.</hi> 4. <hi>ad Amand.</hi> c. <hi>Cyp ep</hi> 66.</note> to offer Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:23794:35"/>yea alſo
<note n="c" place="margin">
                           <hi>Ang. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> feſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>.</hi> 9. <hi>c.</hi> 14.</note> for the dead. And whether therfore there were not beſides Prieſtes, and Deacons, which they ſeeme to retaine (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in the firſt Churches, I ſay) alſo
<note n="d" place="margin">
                           <hi>Euſ l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 35.</note> Subdeaco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, Acolytes, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orciſtes, Lectors, &amp; Oſtiaries, or Dore-keapers, all which they haue plainely laide away? Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther theſe orders were not, I ſay,
<note n="e" place="margin">
                           <hi>Cyp. ep.</hi> 66.</note> in reſpect of a Sacrifice; and there vpon ſo diſtinguished, that although they might all be with in the Chauncell (which the Lay people, were he the King or Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour,
<note n="f" place="margin">
                           <hi>Theod. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 17. <hi>Soz. l.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 24.</note> might not) yet ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might
<note n="g" place="margin">
                           <hi>Dion. Ec. Dion c.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp; ep.</hi> 8. <hi>ad. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moph.</hi>
                        </note> not come at the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, others might: and there,
<note n="h" place="margin">
                           <hi>Hier. in Ezec.</hi> 45.48.</note> ſome able to doe leſſe, others able to doe more? Let them ſay, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they finde not all this in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitie, yea, and that it was the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo obſerued, much more ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:23794:35"/>then we obſerue it now? and therefore, wher as our obſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> plainly sheweth, that we beleue a Sacrifice, and alſo whom we beleeue to be there ſacrificed. ſo, whether the more obſeruation of the ſame in Antiquitie, be not a plainer demoſtrantion, that they alſo then beleeued the ſame? And whether this be not ſo euident, that they alſo, to proue <hi>Chriſt to be GOD,</hi>
                        <note n="i" place="margin">
                           <hi>Euſ. de laud. Conſt. pag.</hi> 384. <hi>Cyp. Teſt. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 16. <hi>Chry. to</hi> 5. <hi>Con. Iud. or.</hi> 2, <hi>co.</hi> 942.</note> obiected this their Prieſthood and Sacrifice to the Iewes &amp; Painims, shewing vnto them, that wheras then both in <hi>Heruſalem,</hi> and in all Nations, both the Iudaical, &amp; alſo pagane Sacrifices, had giuen, and daily did giue place to this Sacrifice, that the ſame (I ſay) was euen ſo promiſed and foretolde by the Prophets
<note n="k" place="margin">
                           <hi>Mal.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 11.</note> of the old teſtament.</p>
                     <p>And therfore aske the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againe,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:23794:36"/>whether by all this it be not eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that they haue changed the prieſthood of the new Teſtament, both becauſe they are made by the Prince: and becauſe they are not made for the Altare, or to offer Sacrifice? As it is alſo euident, onely by this that they go about to change the name of Prieſtes. For as the Apoſtles bringing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the wolde a new Order, chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the olde names of the Iewes and Gentiles, to witte, <hi>Pontifex</hi> and <hi>Sacerdos</hi> (for which we haue no English) and ſaid for them, <hi>Epiſcopus</hi> and <hi>Preſbyter,</hi> whereof are deriued our English names <hi>Bishop</hi> and <hi>Prieſte:</hi> ſo, who ſeeth not, that the Heretikes changing again thoſe Apoſtolike names in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Superintendent</hi> and <hi>Elder,</hi> doe manifeſtly bewray them ſelues, that they haue alſo changed the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:23794:36"/>Apoſtolike Order? And that wee who are found ſtill to haue retei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Apoſtolike names, haue therefore neuer gone aboute to change the Apoſtolike Order? In ſo much that wheras we (as they know) accompte their Orders, no Orders: yet they accepte our Orders for true Orders, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing bene Ordered by vs, ſeeke not to be reordered, as may be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in <hi>Parker, Grindall, Sandes, Horne,</hi> and many moe that are Prieſtes of the Catholicke ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king.</p>
                     <p>And herevpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may al men note how it is: that wheras aforetime, Hereſies haue troubled the world vnder the name of chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, theſe men haue brought in not ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly an Hereſie, but (as it may rather be called) <hi>an Apoſtaſie,</hi> from almoſt all the Law of Chriſt. For
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:23794:37"/>as <hi>Sainte Paule</hi> ſaieth. Vpon the changing of <hi>Sacerdotium,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 12.</note> that is to ſaye Orders (or Peieſthoode) there muſt needes folow chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Law. bycauſe the Law runneth ſo much vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Prieſts as is to be noted both in <hi>Moyſes</hi> Iudaicall law, &amp; alſo in our Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> law: which one thing I would to God they wold quietly, ſadly, and with the feare of God conſider: that they I (ſay) go about to do againſt Chriſt and his law, as much almoſt, as the <hi>Turke,</hi> if he should come, would do? and where he cometh, doth?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="25" type="demand">
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 25. <hi>Demaund Monkes.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THEN whether they be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Euſ. hiſt. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 15.16</note> that the matter be tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed betweene vs by the Religion of the Monkes, Nunnes, Ermites
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:23794:37"/>Anchoretes,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Soz. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 12.13.14. <hi>l.</hi> 3 <hi>c.</hi> 12.13.15. <hi>l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 15.17.28.</note> and other ſuch like perſons in ſtate of perfection, that were in thoſe firſt tymes of the church of Chriſt? Yea whether it be not a plaine confounding of them, and their doings, to heare that then alſo, as euer ſithens,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Aug. de moribus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ec. cat. c.</hi> 31 <hi>&amp; de vn Ec. c.</hi> 14.</note> there were ſuch perſons in the church of Chriſt, ſpecially to ſee that
<note n="a" place="margin">
                           <hi>Euſ. de lau, Conſt. p.</hi> 385.</note> chriſtian writers haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Painimes made of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for their ſtraight life and great numbers, an argument to proue Chriſtes diuinity?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="26" type="demand">
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 26. <hi>Demaund. Fathers.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>VVETHER they will be tryed by the fayth, and Religion, of the ancient Fathers? Or, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther euer any refuſed to be ſo tryed, but onely Heretikes? Or, whether the Fathers Faith and
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:23794:38"/>Religion, were not the faith, and Religion of all the church in their ſeuerall tymes? Or whether the Fathers were not all of one faith, of one church, and of one religion? Or, whether theſe (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides many moe) be not good cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes for chriſtian men to beleeue the Fathers, in ſo much, that the Proteſtantes themſelues thinke it good, and neceſſary, to make a shew of the fathers in their books and ſermons, vnto the people?</p>
                     <p>But yet let them ſay in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, whether they were not al of our church, and of our religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Or els, why do they put vs to defend their authority? Why do they in writing and ſpeaking (as moſt men know) ſo derogate fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their credite? yea let them ſay, whether they were not all Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops or Prieſtes of our churches
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:23794:38"/>making (which I touched a little before) and many of them alſo Monkes, as
<note n="a" place="margin">
                           <hi>Soz. l.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 15. <hi>Ruf. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 28.</note> 
                        <hi>S. Baſil, S. Gregory Nazianzen,</hi>
                        <note n="b" place="margin">
                           <hi>Hier proae. l.</hi> 4. <hi>in Iere.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>S. Hierome,</hi>
                        <note n="c" place="margin">
                           <hi>Aug. ep.</hi> 89. <hi>q.</hi> 4. <hi>&amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Petil. l.</hi> 3 <hi>cap.</hi> 40.</note> 
                        <hi>S. Augustine,</hi>
                        <note n="d" place="margin">
                           <hi>Greg dial. l.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 55.</note> 
                        <hi>S. Gregory,</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi>
                        <note n="e" place="margin">
                           <hi>Paul ep.</hi> 7. <hi>ad Seu.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>S. Paulinus,</hi> and many others? And theſe, and all the reſt (I ſay) of one religion, and therefore no one of them all of the Proteſtants religion: and therefore againe, the church at no tyme of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants religion?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="27" type="demand">
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 27. <hi>Demande. Councells.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>VVHETHER they know not that their Religion hath been of late examined diligently, and finally condemned, and ours confirmed in the Generall coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Trent? And, whether euer any refuſed to yeald to a General councell, but onely Heretikes?
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:23794:39"/>And, whether they can giue any iuſt cauſe, why me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> should beleue that in old tyme Generall coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels might with authority define and determine of faith and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, &amp; this councell might not?</p>
                     <p>Yea, whether not only this, but alſo any other General coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, were euer holden by Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantes, or for Proteſtantes: and not all, as well as this, by men of our church, and for our church, as by Bishops that were made af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter our manner aforſayd, many of them being alſo Monkes, and all of the ſame religion with Monks hauing there alſo their Deacons and Subdeacons, and Acolytes, &amp;c. waiting vpon them: and no one of them euer that marryed, or thought it lawfull to marry, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that he was made a Bishop? Beſides many other pointes of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:23794:39"/>their doctrine alſo, that may for vs againſt the Proteſtantes be noted in the actes of thoſe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celles? Finally, if euer any ſuch councell were for them, let them tell vs, why they write &amp; ſpeake ſo much againſt all councells, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelling vs to defend their autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity? and yet let them ſay, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all other catholike Bishops, and all the church, were not, at thoſe ſeuerall tymes, of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels religion: and all thoſe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels of one religion: and therfore the church neuer of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants religion?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="28" type="demand">
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 28. <hi>Demaund. Sea Apoſtolike.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>VVHETHER they confeſſe not, that we at this tyme do beleeue, and communicate with the ſea Apoſtolike of the church
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:23794:40"/>of Rome? Whether Catholickes did not alwaies ſo doe? Whether euer any refuſed obſtinately ſo to doe,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Opt. l.</hi> 2. <hi>frl.</hi> 15. <hi>Vict. de perſec. Vand. l.</hi> 2 <hi>fol.</hi> 20. <hi>Auguſt. cou. ep. Fund. c.</hi> 4.</note> but onely Schiſmatikes and Heretickes? Whether the holy Fathers by their ſo doing, did not vſe to confounde al Heretickes &amp; to shew thereby, that they did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue and communicate with <hi>S. Peter</hi> &amp; <hi>S. Paule?</hi> Away, as, moſt eaſy, ſo continually moſt ſure and certaine, to auoide all error.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="29" type="demand">
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 29. <hi>Demaund. Traditions.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>VVHE THER they wilbe tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s moſt certaine that haue bene alwaies in the Church of Chriſt? Yea, whether it be not a plaine ouerthrowing of all theire buildinge, onely to heare, that there haue bene al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies ſuche Traditions in the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:23794:40"/>Church of Chriſt? Or let them ſay whether theyfind not in moſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued Antiquitie ſuch Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons?
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Chryſoſ. hom.</hi> 69. <hi>ad popul. Antioc. Cyp. ep.</hi> 63. <hi>Aug. ep.</hi> 118. <hi>c.</hi> 6.</note> Or whether they find any ſuch Tradition making for them, and not for vs? Or whether euer any denied obſtinately all Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, crying in euery thing for on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture, but only Heretiks?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="30" type="demand">
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 30. <hi>Demaunde. Their owne doctors</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>VVETHER they will be tried by their owne Doctors, and Felowes, as by <hi>Luther, Caluine,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Lib. in Zuing. an.</hi> 1545</note> and ſuch like? And whether they know not, that <hi>Luther</hi> hath writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten many Bookes full bitterly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, and condemned the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to Hell, becauſe they be Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries, denying the real pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Chriſtes Body in the B. Sacrament? And that <hi>Caluine</hi>
                        <pb n="80" facs="tcp:23794:41"/>likewiſe calleth it a blaſphemie, to geue to the King,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>In Amos</hi> 7.</note> (and much more to a Quene) the Headship or Primacie of the CHVRCH of England? And therfore aske the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, with what co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, yea &amp; with what face they can ſay theirs to be the true Church, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelleth men ſo to blaſpheme, and that with booke othe: their felow Puritanes at home alſo abhorring it? That I ſpeake not of many other pointes alſo of their Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, condemned alſo by theire owne felowes, as they know the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, &amp; whoſoeuer els that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth their Bookes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="31" type="demand">
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 31. <hi>Demaund. Vniuerſalitie.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>WHETHER they know not,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>vin. Lyr con. om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> c.</hi> 3.4.31.41. <hi>Opt. l.</hi> 2 <hi>f</hi> 13. <hi>Bed. Hiſt.</hi> 4.5 <hi>c.</hi> 16.</note> that the Auncient Fathers haue taught vs in ſuch a doubtfull
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:23794:41"/>time of Hereſie as this is, to trie out the truth by Vniuerſalitie: &amp; that they meane thereby; if at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny time we ſee a piece of Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome diuide it ſelf fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the whole, that wee folow then the whole (the Vniuerſalitie, (I ſay, of the Church in our owne time) and not the piece. Aske the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantes now, if this had bene done in <hi>Luthers</hi> time, whom shoulde Chriſtan men haue folowed, <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> or the <hi>Pope?</hi> And if the <hi>Pope</hi> then, now alſo the <hi>Pope</hi> pardie; <hi>Gregorie</hi> the thirtenth that now is, agreing in all (as they know) with <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth that was the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Aske the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Finally, whether they ſinge not therfore againſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in <hi>Te Deum,</hi> when they ſay, <hi>Te per orbem terrarum ſancta confitetur Eccleſia,</hi> which is to ſay, that the faith or confeſſion of
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:23794:42"/>the vniuerſall Church, that is the true confeſſion?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="32" type="demand">
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 32. <hi>Demaund. Antiquitie.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>VVHETHER they know not that the ſame Fathers haue taught vs,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Vine. Lyr c.</hi> 3.4.6.7.8.9.38.41.</note> for trying out of Truth to look likewiſe vnto Antiquitie? and that, as by Vniuerſalitie they meane our owne time, ſo by An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity, they meane the time that was before our owne time: tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching vs therfore by this, if in our owne time any Noueltie do raign and that perhaps vniuerſally, that then we haue reſpecte to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer time, before ſuch Noueltie did ariſe? Aske the Proteſtantes then, whether they be content ſo to do? And whether three ſcore yeeres ago, before <hi>Luther</hi> aroſe, Chriſtendome were of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion?
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:23794:42"/>yea, whether it were not of our Religion, both then, and many hundred yeeres afore; and that, by their owne confeſſion?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="33" type="demand">
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 33. <hi>Demaund. Conſent</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>VVHETHER the ſame Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers haue not taught vs, to trie out Truth by Conſent alſo. And,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Vin. Lyr. c.</hi> 3.4.8.10.11.38.41. <hi>Bed. hist. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 25</note> whether they meane not thereby, that ſuppoſing both the Vniuerſalitie of our owne time, were corrupt, &amp; alſo the Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of former time, were at vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, we should the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue an eie to Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent in Antiquitie. As if there had bin of olde ſome one Father or ſome one Prouinciall Councel for the Proteſtants (as yet there was not) to ſee the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whether there were not ſome General Councel againſt them? Aske them now,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:23794:43"/>whether that before <hi>Luther</hi> was borne, there were not many Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Councells, yea all Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Councells againſt them? and yet neither any Prouincial Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, nor ſo much as any one Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor for any one thing that they hold againſt vs?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="34" type="demand">
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 34. <hi>Demaund. Authoritie.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>VVHETHER the Church of Chriſt did not euermore take her ſelfe to be of Authoritie irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fragable, and ſo beare her ſelfe, as neceſſarie &amp; worthie to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued vpon her onelyword; and therfore no man to controll her
<note n="a" place="margin">
                           <hi>Aug. ep.</hi> 105.</note> Sentence or Iudgement, no man to miſdoubt her
<note n="b" place="margin">
                           <hi>Aug ep.</hi> 118: <hi>c.</hi> 3. <hi>&amp; ep</hi> 105.</note> Practiſe? And whether S. <hi>Augustine</hi> haue not written a booke therupon, which he calleth. <hi>De vtilitate credendi;</hi>
                        <pb n="85" facs="tcp:23794:43"/>
                        <hi>Of the vtilitie of beleeuing</hi> the Church in all thinges: shewing how profitable, how neceſſary, &amp; how ſure a way that is, for the fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding out of true Religion? And, whether the <hi>Maniches</hi> then, as the Proteſtantes now, founde not fault with that way? And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the true Chriſtians, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, did not for all that hold the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt thoſe &amp; all other He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retickes vpon the Churches Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie:
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Chriſ. con. gent. de S. Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> coll.</hi> 882. 884. <hi>Et con. Iud. ar.</hi> 2. <hi>col</hi> 928. <hi>Euſ Hist l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 3. <hi>Devt. or c.</hi> 14.</note> yea and alleage it alſo vnto the Iewes and Painimes, to proue that Chriſt is God, and that the holy Scriptures, with the Miracles and all other things in them contained, be true: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe (I ſay) the Church or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of the Chriſtians ſo ſaith and ſo beleeueth? And, whether <hi>Saint Auguſtine,</hi> and that by true rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, doth not infer therupon, that,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:23794:44"/>ſeeing we beleeue Chriſt and the Scriptures, becauſe of the church, we muſt therfore beleeue the Church in all other thinges alſo, whatſoeuer it ſaieth againſt the Heretickes?</p>
                     <p>And, whether this Authoritie do not therefore argue, that the Church can neuer erre? And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neuer erring doe not argue, that it can neuer perish. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore again, whether it do not now alſo well &amp; worthely claime the ſame authoritie? Yea, whether the Proteſtants themſelues haue not receaued many thinges, as Chriſt himſelfe, and the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures themſelues, &amp;c. vpon our churches credite; the church (I ſay) that now is? Aske them then howe they can poſſiblye bee the church, who willingly doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the claime of ſuch Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:23794:44"/>and doe by their doings, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe it to be in the companie of their aduerſaries? Finally bydde the deceaued conſider this well, that they haue no forte or nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of men amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt them, whom they may truſte in all thinges; with whom, and in whoſe ſteppes they may venture to walke the way of Faith and Religion towardes ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</p>
                     <p>None of all the Sectes in our countrey, nor in all the world ſo happie, none ſo ſecure, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no Church amongeſt them: becauſe (I ſay) they openly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the claime of Authoritie, confeſſing therby that it is not of them that the Creed ſaith: <hi>I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue the Church:</hi> in ſo much that they haue ſuffered of late <hi>an vnle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arned Christian</hi> (as he is called) to ſet out in Print, a vaine libell
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:23794:45"/>
                        <hi>againste the Aucthoritie of the Church of God,</hi> comparing and oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing vnto it, <hi>the Authority of the word of God,</hi> as though the word of God, and the Church of God, were one againſt the other: it being yet ſo plainely written, that as the Father ſaied of his Sonne:
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 17. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.</note> 
                        <hi>Ipſum audite, Heare him.</hi> So the Sonne ſaid of his church: <hi>Si Eccleſiam non audierit, ſit tibi ficut Ethnicus &amp; Publicanus: If he will not heare the Church, do thou vſe him, (as the Iewes did) as an Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then and a Publican.</hi> And yet this felow truſteth ſo much in his owne folie,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Prou.</hi> 17</note> that he is bold to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke all catholiks to anſwere his childishnes, or els they muſt be accounted (ſaith he) no leſſe then very Murderers. It were good for him, poore man, that he had in him no more pride then lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:23794:45"/>My beſt counſaile to him for his ſaluation is, that he reade humblye theſe Demaundes, and looke whether any of his greate Maſters will anſwere them. And if after this, his ſtomacke ſerue him ſtill, let him ſet out his Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel more orderly with his name, &amp; with approbation of their Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins, and with priuiledge, that we labour not in vaine: &amp; with the grace of God he shall quickly ſee it anſwered, as vnworthy as it is.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="35" type="demand">
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 35. <hi>Demand. Vnity.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THEN whether vnity proced not of the ſayd Authority: And, our Church therefore one for euer, and not poſſibly by any queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or controuerſy to be deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratly deuided within it ſelfe. They on the other ſide, for lacke
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:23794:46"/>thereof, running euery day into more and more diuiſion amongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, &amp; multiplying Sectes (as all men do ſee) without hold or meaſure: not being able to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leage herein any excuſe for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, which the Arians, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiſtes, &amp; other olde Hereticks might not as well aleage for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe of their diuiſions: yea euen their owne Doctrine, being the very cauſe therof, and they ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore guiltie of all theſe ſectes? that doctrine, I ſay, wherin they teach, that the Scriptures are ſo eaſye, and that therefore euerie one may folow his owne ſeſe, yea and vant alſo that it is the ſence of the Spirite himſelfe?</p>
                     <p>And, whether the Churches inſeparable vnitie be not ſo ſure an argument of Truth, that it is a moſte iuſte Motiue (by Chriſtes
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:23794:46"/>owne ſaying) for the world <hi>to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in Chriſt:</hi> that no man mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, ſeeing the infinite Sects that be now in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, that there be alſo ſo many incredulous that beleeue not in Chriſt?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="36" type="demand">
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 36. <hi>Demaund. Kepers of Scriptures.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>VVHether it were not our Church, that notified to the worlde the <hi>Canon</hi> of the holye Bookes of the new Teſtament? Whether it were not our Church that hath had the cuſtodie &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruing both of the foreſaid, and of the other Bookes of the holy Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, euer ſince the Apoſtles time? Or elſe, whether before this time the Expoſitors thereof were Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants. And whether the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants had not the ſaide Books of vs? And whether they can charge
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:23794:47"/>our Church, all this longe while of her poſſeſion, with adding or minishinge any iote thereof? Or whether they can not bee char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, this short while of their vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation, with robbing vs of many wholle Bookes thereof (Bookes, I ſay, canonized in aproued Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels) and of many a particulare portion more? or whether euer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny coulde be ſo charged, but only Heritikes? Finally, whether our Church therefore be not the o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly true poſſeſſor or keper of this tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſure, as to whom only the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtels co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mited it: and therefore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine ours the only true Church?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="37" type="demand">
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 37. <hi>Demaund. Storehouſe of all Truthe</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>VVHETHER not onely all Canonicall Scripture (as I haue ſaide) but alſo all other
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:23794:47"/>truthes agreed vpon at any time by the Church of God, and as it were laide vp for euer, are not at this tym to be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in our church? as, that which was agreed vpon againſt the Arians, that which was concluded againſt the Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſtes, briefly that which was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined aganſt all other Heretikes? Aſke them whether it haue not bene hither vnto, and whether it be not ſtill? ſafelye keapt in our Church? And, how them ſelues came by the ſaide Truthes? whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther otherwiſe then at our Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches handes?</p>
                     <p>Aſke them againe: Whereas ſome auncient writers haue bene iuſtly noted for certaine errors, whether our Church may be tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with any of thoſe errors? yea whether our Churches Faith be not the Rule, whereby both Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:23794:48"/>and all others ſafely may and do now read thoſe wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and ſo moſt eaſilye auoide thoſe errors, being nothinge mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with the authoritie nor anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie of thoſe writers? nor with the greate showe of many Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which either thoſe writers or alſo ſundrye olde Heretikes made for their errors: knowing vndoubtedly by the Rule of our Churches faith, that thoſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures haue not that meaning: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing otherwiſe like to thinke (as any indifferent man will beare me recorde) that the Scriptures make for thoſe olde errors &amp; he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies, no leſſe, yea much more, then for <hi>Luther or Caluine,</hi> or any other Heretikes of our time? And whether it be not plaine by this, that our Church is that <hi>Depoſito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium diues,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iren. l.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 4.</note> 
                        <hi>that Riche Storehouſe,</hi>
                        <pb n="95" facs="tcp:23794:48"/>wherein all Truth either by the Apoſtles, or by any other,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. <hi>d</hi> 14.</note> hath bene laide vp? and wherein euery man that will, may without dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and without labour, finde, what ſoeuer Truth he ſeeketh?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="38" type="demand">
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 38. <hi>Demaund. Old Hereſies.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>VVHETHER on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſide, amongſt the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantes, any other Truth be to be found, but only ſuch as they rece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of vs? yea further, whereas very many Falſehoodes, Errors, &amp; Hereſies haue bene from time to time by the Church noted and condemned, whether a greate number of the ſame Hereſies, be not now to bee founde amongeſt the Proteſtantes? So many olde Hereſies, I ſaye (whereas one were enough to proue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiks)
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:23794:49"/>as be enough to proue them almoſt Apoſtatates. As, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<note n="a" place="margin">
                           <hi>Epip haer.</hi> 75. <hi>Aug. haer</hi> 53.</note> Praying for the dead, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt preſcripte Faſting daies Againſt
<note n="b" place="margin">
                           <hi>Aug to.</hi> 6. <hi>de fide. con. Manich. c.</hi> 9.10. <hi>Aug. haer.</hi> 82. <hi>&amp; Ret l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 22.</note> Free wil Againſt <hi>(c)</hi> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of Single life, Againſt <hi>(c)</hi> the Vow of the ſame, &amp; at leaſt twe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty more. And therefore whether, as our Church is the ſtorehouſe of Truth, ſo their Sinagogue bee not the Sinke of falſe hood and of Hereſie?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="29" type="demand">
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 29. <hi>Demaund. VVhere grew their doctrine.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>AGAINE, whether the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that of olde profeſſed the ſaid pointes of theſe mens do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and were of the Church therfore noted for Heretiks, were not alſo otherwiſe moſt notorious Heretickes: for certaine other pointes I ſay, confeſſed alſo by
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:23794:49"/>the Proteſtants to be hereſy. As whether
<note n="a" place="margin">
                           <hi>Epip haer.</hi> 75. <hi>Aug. haer</hi> 52.</note> 
                        <hi>Aerius</hi> who held with them againſt praying, and offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ring for the dead, and againſt all the preſcript faſting dayes, were not beſides that alſo an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian: &amp; the like of all their other Parteners? Aske them now what it meaneth, that their doctrine alwayes hath been found in ſuch naughty ground, and with ſuch ſtinking weedes: And contrary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe our doctrine touching the ſame pointes, found alſo at the ſame tyme in ſuch as they confeſſe themſelues to haue beene good ground, as in S. <hi>Augustine,</hi> in S. <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> and others, who did ſo hold our ſayed doctrine, that they with the whole Church co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned <hi>Aerius</hi> of hereſy, for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying the ſame.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="40" type="demand">
                     <pb n="98" facs="tcp:23794:50"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 40. <hi>Demand. They neuer afore new.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>VVHETHER of this it follow not, that they muſt needes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe, that their church was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in the world, neuer (I ſay) at no tyme, before this our tyme? Or elſe let them ſay, whether one that is an Arrian, denying Godes Sonne to be <hi>Conſubſtantiall</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>Of the ſame ſubstance with his Father,</hi> may be of their Church. Yea alſo of <hi>VViclef,</hi> and <hi>Huſſe</hi> themſelues do you aske the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, how they could be of this their Church, holding with Pelagius Iuſtification
<note n="a" place="margin">
                           <hi>Tho. wald. to.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. <hi>Melanct. hom. ad Friden. Micon.</hi>
                        </note> by mans owne merits; and alſo
<note n="b" place="margin">
                           <hi>Heu Syl. in hiſt. Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>he. c.</hi> 35.</note> that a King or Queene committing any mortall ſinne, leeſeth ſtreight his office, and is no longer to be obied?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="41" type="demand">
                     <pb n="99" facs="tcp:23794:50"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 41. <hi>Demaund. Studying all Truth.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>VVETHER our Church, to keepe ſafely all Truth in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner aforeſayd: doe not diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtuddy all Truth: her Maſters therefore, in their Bookes, and Schooles, teaching all Truth, &amp; her ſcholers therfore learning all Truth: to defend (I ſay) all Truth of Chriſt, againſt all ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes, againſt Painyms, againſt Iewes, and againſt all Hereſyes? And whether Proteſtantes, on the contrary ſide, &amp; but a few of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (God wot) do ſtudy any more then a few queſtions of this tyme onely, and that ſo lightly, that they be afrayd to reaſon with common Catholickes: Being all rather occupyed about wyuing, and thriuing in the world, then
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:23794:51"/>ſincerely and learnedly to defend Religion. Or let them tell vs, why elſe our Countrey is ſo ful of Atheiſts, Achriſtes, and all kinds of moſt deteſtable heretikes? Aske them, whether in their vniuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes they haue the whole courſe of Diuinity, within a certaine tearme of yeares, yea or <hi>in Anno Platonis</hi> (proceding as they do) all read ouer? Yea, whether their Students, or Doctours alſo, and Readers can tel you almoſt, what the courſe of diuinity meaneth? And againe aske them, who for chriſtian ſtudy, and increaſe of godly knowledg fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded thoſe v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſityes, builded thoſe Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and inſtituted thoſe degrees of learning, whether our Church or theirs, and who hath authority to make Doctours of Diuinity? whether Kinges and Queens, or
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:23794:51"/>only Bishops? And therefore, if our Church haue againe taken from them her graunt, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nullated their degrees (as it
<note n="a" place="margin">
                           <hi>Bulla Pij</hi> 5. <hi>Anno</hi> 1564.</note> hath done) aske them, by what title they will clayme the ſame?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="42" type="demand">
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 42. <hi>Demaunde. Vnſent.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>VVHETHER the Preachers euer of the Church of Chriſt did take vpon them to preach and teach, without
<note n="a" place="margin">
                           <hi>Ioa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> 20. <hi>c.</hi> 21 <hi>Act.</hi> 15. <hi>cap.</hi> 24. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10 <hi>cap.</hi> 15.</note> ſending. And whether euer any all this while had authority to ſend forth Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, but only the Apoſtles and their Succeſſors, and ſuch as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued it of them?</p>
                     <p>And if they ſay, their ſending to be extraordinary: aske the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, why all this tyme God did ſo ſend non other, but only to barre ſuch as they be from ſo ſaying? Aske the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <pb n="102" facs="tcp:23794:52"/>likewiſe, where then be their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles? Or whether any, alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſtes Church beganne, were ſent out of order, without the gift of Miracles, or of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy, or of both? Finally, you may aske them, what warrant they haue to hold ſuch an office of a Lay Prince? Or how with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out that office, they can pretend to be the true Church of Chriſt?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="43" type="demand">
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 43. <hi>Demaund. Succeſsion.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>VVHETHER it be not eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in the
<note n="a" place="margin">
                           <hi>Act.</hi> 1. <hi>d</hi> 21. <hi>&amp;</hi> 14. <hi>d</hi> 22.</note> Actes and
<note n="b" place="margin">
                           <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. <hi>b.</hi> 5.</note> Epiſtles of the Apoſtles, with the
<note n="c" place="margin">
                           <hi>Euſ. l.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 13.15.23. <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 2.4.10</note> Eccleſiaſticall hiſtoryes of the tymes that followed, that the Church once begunne by and in the Apoſtles, did afterward grow on (as Chriſt
<note n="d" place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat</hi> 13. <hi>c.</hi> 14. <hi>f.</hi> 4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>6. <hi>c.</hi> 18.</note> did promiſe that it should) and ſpread it ſelfe ouer
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:23794:52"/>all places, and through all ages, by Succeſſion? And, whether our church cannot shew in plaine au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenticall writing the continuall Succeſſion of her Bishopes and Paſtors, with their flockes, euer ſince the Apoſtles time? Or, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Proteſtants Church can doe the like. Yea, whether they can in our Countrey referre them ſelues, any further, then to the letters patents of the Prince? And whether this haue not bene
<note n="e" place="margin">
                           <hi>Opt. l.</hi> 2. <hi>f.</hi> 15. <hi>Hier. in Mic.</hi> 1. <hi>Aug. in Pſa. con. par. Do. nat.</hi>
                        </note> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies vſed as a marke moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, to knowe the true Church from Schiſmatikes and Heretikes euen in the
<note n="f" place="margin">3. <hi>Reg.</hi> 12. <hi>g.</hi> 31.</note> Olde Teſtament alſo?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="44" type="demand">
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 44. <hi>Demaund. Apoſtolike Church.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>VHHETHER in the Creede, that we in our Maſſe, and they in their Communion do vſe,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:23794:53"/>this word <hi>Apostolicall,</hi> were or could be put in as a plaine marke to know the Church which we muſt beleeue, but only as it di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recteth vs to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſeeing by experience, that all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Apoſtolicall Churches,
<note place="margin">Trent. de praeſ. Har.</note> are now fayled? Or whether the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church be not Apoſtolicall, as being the Sea of the two moſt glorious &amp; chiefe Apoſtles,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iren. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 3. <hi>Opt l.</hi> 2. <hi>Aug ep.</hi> 165.</note> S. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> and S. <hi>Paul?</hi> Or whether in tyme of ſchiſme and hereſy, the Fathers in their tymes hauing many Seas Apoſtolike, did not chiefly looke themſelues, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect others, to the Apoſtolike Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> shewing therby that the Truth was theirs, becauſe the Bishop of <hi>Rome</hi> that came of the Apoſtles by lineall ſucceſſion, was theirs? And therfore whether we haue not iuſt cauſe to followe
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:23794:53"/>their example, ſpecially ſeeing that Sea ſtill hold on and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue (as the Fathers ſaid it should) to the number now of two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and thirtie Bishopes,
<note place="margin">Aug. in pſ. cont. part. Don.</note> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as to thoſe Fathers time there were not fourtie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="45" type="demand">
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 45. <hi>Demaund. Changinge.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>VVHETHER we haue not yet againe iuſte cauſe to keepe vs with the Churche of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſeeing that the <hi>Romanes</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer changed their Faith, which
<note n="a" place="margin">
                           <hi>Act.</hi> 2. <hi>g.</hi> 31. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10 <hi>c.</hi> 12. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6. 17. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16. <hi>c.</hi> 19.</note> they receiued of <hi>S. Peter &amp; S. Paul?</hi> Which is ſo plaine, that I appeale to the Proteſtants them ſelues, whether the Romans did not (for example) <hi>Pray for the dead,</hi> euen then when thoſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers aforeſaid did auouch that they were vncha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged: yea ſo won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ring,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:23794:54"/>euen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo, <hi>at Aeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> for denying the ſame, that to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather with all other Churches they condemned him as an Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike, for going about to change that which alwaies vnitll then they had keapte vnchanged: as they doe keepe it ſtil, both that &amp; all the reſt: and that, by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtantes owne confeſſion, theſe thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d or twelue hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred years? Whereby no wiſe man can doubt but that they remaine alſo the reſt, vp to the Apoſtles time alſo, without change. Yea to conſider no more but that ſince <hi>Luthers</hi> time, the <hi>Popes</hi> haue not changed one iote, and that the Heretickes (on the other ſide) haue not ſince then lefte, nor do not leaue chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging euery daye, may to any man of indifferent iudgement ſeeme a demonſtration, that the <hi>Popes</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:23794:54"/>at all did chang. And as for one or two amongſt all the <hi>Popes</hi> whom they charge with erring: firſt we deny it, for it is moſt falſe, as the learned Catholikes haue well declared. Secondly we ſay, ſuppoſing ſome <hi>Popes</hi> had erred, yet neuer did any <hi>Pope</hi> goe about to chang the <hi>Romans</hi> faith with his error. Thirdely we ſay, and let the wiſe conſider it well, that were it ſo, thoſe <hi>Popes</hi> did erre, &amp; alſo goe aboute to infect the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> with thoſe errors, yet is it not thoſe errors, wherewith the Proteſtantes do now charge the <hi>Pope</hi> &amp; the <hi>Romanes.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they blaſphemouſly bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den <hi>S. Liberius</hi> with <hi>Arrianiſme,</hi> or any other with the like, they might better holde their peace, then ſo to lie, &amp; yet their lye no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all vnto the purpoſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="46" type="demand">
                     <pb n="108" facs="tcp:23794:55"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 46. <hi>Demaund. Our Aunceſtors ſaued.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THEN whether al this while that they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe our church to haue bene, at leaſt 12 hundred yeeres, they will ſay, that all our and their fathers &amp; mothers gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d fathers and grandmothers, and other Annceſtors, Kinſefolke &amp; Countreimen, and all others that haue gonne ſo long for Chriſtian men,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iustin. l.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 2 <hi>in fine c</hi>
                        </note> are all da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned in Hell? yea, whether <hi>Caluine</hi> him ſelfe do not confeſſe the contrarie, that our Church (I ſay) ſerued well the turne all this while to ſaue men from Hell, and to bringe men to Heauen? Aske them then, why it cannot ſerue ſtill that turne as wel? Or if they ſay, that ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce afore did excuſe, &amp; now (becauſe of their preaching) it cannot aske
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:23794:55"/>them, why they do confeſſe that <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> and ſuch like, are of all moſt ſurely ſaued, who yet had not this ignorance, but knew right well their new doctrine (as in <hi>Aerius, Iouinianus, Vigilanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, &amp;c</hi>) and conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned it for moſt wicked Hereſie? And therefore whether it be not wiſdome for al men to hold the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtill in our chuch or to returne againe vnto it?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="47" type="demand">
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 47. <hi>Demaund. Communion of Saintes</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>ALSO whether their church as it neuer was in the world before now, ſo now at theire firſt appearing haue not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny moſt foule abſurdities, in pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching vp it ſelfe ſo narowly into the ſtreightes of one ſmall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, that in it one Chriſtian man to another, euen in ſpirituall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires is a ſtranger? that in it an Eccleſiaſticall and Apoſtolicall
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:23794:56"/>power erected by Chriſt, is dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med a foreiner: that in it any Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Councell that euer was or euer can be gathered of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops of other Nations of al chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dom, yea or of their owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federats, can take, beare, or haue no whit of authoritie: that in it Epiſtles directed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beyond the Sea by S. <hi>Paule</hi> himſelfe, if he were aliue, ſuch as his Epiſtles to the Romanes, Corinthians &amp;c, could beare no ſway: that in it all the Apoſtles togither writing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their Synode of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> as they did to the <hi>Antiochians,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Act.</hi> 15.</note> might beare no ſtroake: that in it Chriſt himſelfe without the King and the Parliaments conſent, might not diſpoſe of his own churches: but hold his peace and leaue his medling (like a Foreiner as he was) vnleſſe he would ſay, that he
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:23794:56"/>were the naturall King of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, and diſplace the lawefull heires of the Kinges afore time: becauſe by their ſaying that head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship cannot be ſeparated from the kingshipe, being (as they ſay) a real, naturall, and eſſential parte therof: and therfore they shoulde not write the King of Englande, <hi>Head of the Church of England,</hi> no not <hi>vnder Chriſt,</hi> vnleſſe they wold write him alſo <hi>King of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land vnder Christ.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Of many other their abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Conf. l.</hi> 9 <hi>c.</hi> 12.24</note> as that <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> there (with our Prieſtes doeing his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt) should forfeite an hundred Markes for ſaying Maſſe for his Mothers ſoule, &amp;c. I here ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="33" type="demand">
                     <pb n="112" facs="tcp:23794:57"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 33. <hi>Demaund. VVhere Chriſt worketh.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>VVHETHER it be not our Church onely, which now, and euer, is ſo bleſſed of God, and ſo embrued with Chriſtes Blood, that she hath grace in her Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments (as well for remiſſion of ſinnes after Baptiſme, as of ſinnes before Baptiſme; to the vnſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able comfort of all that be heauy loaden) merite in her workes, force in her word, power in her teaching, ſo that shee breedeth deuotion, turneth to Religion, &amp; to the ſearch of ſaluation, ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly altereth the hartes of men: yea her children therfore being the ſaddeſt ſorte of people, men of beſt order in all families, townes, and citties, for all goodnes beſt belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued both of God and man. And whether with the Proteſtantes,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:23794:57"/>all be not cleane contrarie: No preaching of Penance, no grace in Sacraments, nothing but ſinne in good workes although they be done in Chriſt, no power to bring vnder Diuels, no bleſſing no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte. And their folowers therfore eaſie to be noted by their ill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions: All perſons as they fall from order and godlineſſe, more neare they become to their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: a generall obſeruation, that all men, as they returne to our Church, bettered and amended; as they fall to their Synagogue, much worſed &amp; more then afore corrupted. And yet be they neuer ſo wicked &amp; flagitious, haue they <hi>Onely Faith,</hi> and (no doubt) they shall be ſaued. And what Faith, I pray you? Not our Chriſtian faith, which is conteined in the articles of our Creed, and ſuch
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:23794:58"/>like: but a ſpeciall Faith, or an vndoubted perſwaſion that he is predeſtinate. For who ſoeuer ſo perſwadeth him ſelfe, doubting no more therof the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he doth of one God, and of Chriſts birth &amp; death and other Articles of the Creed: he (they ſay) moſt certainly is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtinate and shall be ſaued, and his ſinnes are thereby remitted. And it is (forſooth) a goodly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable way, becauſe it teacheth men to bee ſoe certaine. But in truth and in deed (if it be a litle examined) no greater teaching of vncertaintie. For (ſay we vnto them) not onely English Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantes, but alſo any wicked man co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuing in his wickednes, may firmely perſuade him ſelfe that he is predeſtinate, and all other Heretiks of this time do ſo teach and ſo perſuade them ſelues, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <pb n="115" facs="tcp:23794:58"/>thoſe two Anabaptiſtes alſo who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nable creatures, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues of late did burne in Smithfielde. How the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> teach you, that the ſaid faith or perſuaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaueth all? here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto they ſay, that ſuch Heretiks and wicked perſons can not haue this wonderfull faith: becauſe it cannot be without true doctrine nor without good workes. But (ſay we) they perſuade the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues? and they will ſweare, yea and die in it, yea (and which is greateſt of al) they know, that they ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues: as who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not, when he perſuadeth him ſelfe of any thing, as of One God of Chriſt, and ſo forth; O ſay our Proteſtants (and the like ſay the others of them to) but they do not ſoe perſwade them ſelues. And where (I pray you) is now becom this great certaintie? the matter
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:23794:59"/>being brought now to this paſſe, that (by their owne ſaying of one another) no man can tell when he is certaine: in ſo much that alſo of any one of their owne fellowes ſtanding now in true doctrine (as they eſteeme it) &amp; in good works and ſo perſuading himſelfe to be predeſtinate; if he fall hereafter, they muſt then and wil ſay of him that he did not afore perſuade him ſelfe: and ſo none of them all can ſay to day that he is certayne, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he cannot tell what he shall doe to morrow. Is not here then (trow you) a greate certaintie? (that I vſe no other reaſon againſt this vaine &amp; ſinfull point of their doctrine, being yet the grounde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worke of all theire innouations.) Well, whatſoeuer they ſay, eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man ſeeth, that all Heretikes &amp; naughtie packes may, and that
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:23794:59"/>ſome of euery ſorte do thus per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade &amp; aſſure themſelues. And we (on the otherſide) be ſure, (&amp; that not by our only bare perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, as they ſee by this Booke) that none of them all ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuing shall be ſaued. And therfore beſt it were for them to confeſſe the vanitie of their new ſpecial faith, and to returne to the Catholicke faith, and ſo liuing through the grace of Chriſt in good workes, to hope aſſuredly for ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of now moſt vainely they do pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume: or rather in deed they nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hope nor preſume, but think verely that there is no ſaluation at all, vſing therfore their owne religion, as if they thought it, and as it is indeed, no religion at all, as now at length the wiſer ſorte &amp; principall of the Realme haue proued infinite waies by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:23794:60"/>of their doinges, according to our Sauiours true prophecie,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.</note> 
                        <hi>Ex fructibus eorum cognoſcetis eos. By their fruites, you shall knowe them.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="49" type="demand">
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 49. <hi>Demaund. All enemies.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>VVHETHER it bee not our Church onely, which al the enemies of Chriſt do fight againſt conſpiring all againſt vs, as the companie that onely ſtandeth in their way, &amp; that onely beareth off their brunte: ſpecially all Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctes, and Hereſies for that cauſe bearing intollerably with one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nothers blaſphemies, and (as it is called) ſyncretizing, and tyed togither by the tailes (like <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> Foxes) their heades being moſt farre a ſunder,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iud.</hi> 15.</note> and counting Turkes and Iewes and very A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſtes,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:23794:60"/>for their frendes, and all that be not Papiſtes. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, whether our Church be not the true Church and our Church onely: as which only, both now, and euer, hath bene of all malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, &amp; by Hel gates impugned.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="50" type="demand">
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 50. <hi>Demaund. Sure to continue.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>VVHETHER our Church, for all this fighting and conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring againſt it,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Aug: de vt: cred. c.</hi> 8 <hi>&amp; Pſa. con. part. Do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Chri. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Gent: quod Christus ſit Deus col.</hi> 1039</note> as it hath hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto ſtood vpright, ſo be not ſure to ſtande and continue likewiſe hereafter? Or els, how is it, that the Fathers, which in their ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry times haue bene bould ſo to ſay of the Church, &amp; namely al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that it (I ſay) should ſtand foreuer, could not all this while be proued liars?
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:23794:61"/>yea whereas they haue further ſaide, that the Church by oppug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> should not o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly not be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>com: but alſo more increaſe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by and florish: Whether this ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of theirs, as alwaies hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſo now likwiſe be not plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly iuſtified: innumirable perſons, as well of our owne countrey (&amp; that, againſt all hope of man: but to the gratious ſafetie hither to) no doubt to the wiſe (of the State ſo much maligned by the Puritans) as of others alſo, daily ſeing, and confeſſing, that ours is the true Church, and ours the true Religion, and the Heretiks haue fowely abuſed hitherunto their ignorance: The Heretikes in the meane time, partely by the conuerſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſuch, partly by their continuall diuiding into ſo many ſtrange Sectes, daily diminish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:23794:61"/>and (as all other Heretiks before them) going to nothing. And whether they were not beſt therefore to put vp their pipes, (as <hi>Humfreie</hi> his wiſe Syllogiſmes in his <hi>Onus</hi> or prophecie of the ruine of <hi>Rome</hi>) to holde their barking againſt the Moone, and to leaue with Saul their vaine kicking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the pricke, getting nothing thereby but onely the eternall hurt &amp; deſtruction both of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues &amp; of their folowers?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="51" type="demand">
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 51. <hi>Demaund. Apostaſie.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>LAST of all (to be short, &amp; to cut off many other queſtions of like weight that I could de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund) whether, as in euery one of theſe Demaundes it is euident that they be Heretickes and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducers, ſo in many of them, and
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:23794:62"/>much more in all of them, it bee not likewiſe euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that they be litle better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> plaine Apoſtataes, as?</p>
                     <p>Firſt in changing the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoode,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 12.</note> wherupon the change of al the Lawe enſueth: as, we ſee, they alſo thereupon haue cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged wel neare all, which no olde Heretikes euer durſt to do, except it were the Manichees:
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Orat. de</hi> 5. <hi>Haer. c.</hi> 7.10.6.</note> whom <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> for that cauſe did note to be ſomthing els then Heretiks in ſaying, that there were fiue ſorts of people in the world, <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes Paganes, Manichees, Heretikes</hi> and <hi>Catholickes?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Secondly in reuiuing not one or two, but ſo many olde Hereſies; beſides (as I am bould to ſay) at leaſte a thouſand more of their owne inuention?</p>
                     <p>Thirdly, for taking from Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:23794:62"/>men ſo many arguments of Chriſts God head and Diuinitie: as, the inuiſible Continuance and Authoritie of his Church, the Honour of Croſſes, the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of Croſſes, the Honor of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, the vertue of Relikes, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, Exorciſmes, Vnitie, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice? &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>Fourthly, for leauing nothing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denied, not Fathers, not Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, not Traditions, not Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, nor (the only witneſſe of all Canonical Scripture) the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches authoritie, &amp; departing from the Faith of al ages ſince Chriſts time, agreeing with no Chriſtian time, nor none with them?</p>
                     <p>Fifthly, in place of al Religion and goodnes which they haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued, deuiſing a new goſpel of their foreſaid onely vaine Faith, which teacheth all Sinnes and all
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:23794:63"/>Hereſyes to preſume of ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Beſides much more that I need not to repeate?</p>
                     <p>And whether therefore people now a daies be not to to careleſſe and neglige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of their ſoules, that whereas they shoulde not, vnder paine of euerlaſting damnation, yeald to any one Hereſie, haue ſo fowly yelded to ſo fowle Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie? How beit as <hi>S. Peter</hi> ſaide to the Iewes.
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Act.</hi> 3.</note> 
                        <hi>Et nunc fratres ſcio quia per ignorantiam feciſtis, ſicut &amp; prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipes veſtri:</hi> ſo I doubte not, but that in our Countrey likewiſe many of all ſortes may be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what excuſed by ignorance: and therefore the more hope there is for ſuch as wil repent. But other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe if any for all this, liſt wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to folow on, moſt fowly and moſt miſerably deceauing them ſelues by cauſe afore God they can
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:23794:63"/>not poſſibly haue any excuſe of their ſo doing, no more, then if they should conſent to folow the proceedinges or to frequent the churches of the <hi>Arrians,</hi> or of any other olde Heretikes, yea or of the Turkes them ſelues, if perhappes they liued vnder the raigne of ſuch. And therefore (I ſay) if any liſte to contemne ſtil all holſome counſell, and deſperatelye to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe on, &amp; not to returne to the Truth ſo manifoldly, and ſo plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nely opened? &amp; ſome alſo to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecute it moſte maliciouſſy: their blood, at leaſte wiſe,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ezecb.</hi> 3</note> shal not bee required at our handes hereafter, when they shall repente to late.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:23794:64"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23794:64"/>
                  <p>CERTAINE OTHER DEMANDS ANNEXED TO THE FORMER.</p>
                  <p>VERY FIT Alſo to be propoſed to our En-English Proteſtants, but prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally vnto our Puritans.</p>
                  <p>EXTRACTED <hi>Out of a learned booke, made by the Reu. Fa.</hi> Iohn Hay, <hi>Priest of the Society of Ieſus &amp; propoſed, vnto the Miniſters of Scotland.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>With licence, Anno 1623.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="quotations">
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:23794:65"/>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Stand yee vpon the wayes, and ſee and aske of the old pathes, which is the good way, and walke yee in it, and you shall find refreshing for your ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les.</hi>
                        <bibl>Ieremy 6.16.</bibl>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>There must be hereſyes, that they who are approued, may be knowne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you.</hi>
                        <bibl>Cor.</bibl>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>And I deſire you brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to mark them that make diſſentions and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dals, contrary to the doctrine which you haue learned, and auoyd them: for ſuch do not ſerue Christ our Lord, but their owne belly, and by ſweet ſpeaches and benedictions, ſeduce the harts of innocents.</hi>
                        <bibl>Rom. 16.17.</bibl>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I know that after my departure, there will rauening wolues enter in among you, not ſparing the flocke: and out of your owne ſelues shall ariſe men ſpeaking peruerſe thinges, to draw a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way diſciples after themſelues.</hi>
                        <bibl>Acts 20.29.</bibl>
                     </p>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="preface">
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:23794:65"/>
                  <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
                  <p>GENTLE Reader, by the little experience that I haue in matter of diſputation againſt Protestants, I find the Prouerb to be verifyed, which ſayth: That <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> Aſſe is able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more, then <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> himſelf is able to proue. For the moſt ignorant companion that euer hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a cudgell in ſchoole, makes a shew to be ſome tale and iollie fellow, all the while the skilfull Fencer, ſuffers and wills his young ſchollar to lay at his Maſter, he in the meane tyme lying only at his locke, and defending himſelfe, and not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending his vnskillfull ſchollar. But when this Maiſter, begins to let flye at this ignorant fellow, and to teach him the Art, as well to defend him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, as to offend others, alas, how doe the ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders by laugh at this poore apprentice? To ſee him who ſeemed ſome-body a little before, to be now no-body, and to be knockt and rapt, how, and where his Master listes?</p>
                  <p>The very like is to be ſayd, of the combate or
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:23794:66"/>Controuerſy in Religion, where let Proteſtantes alone, ſtill to ſtricke, obiect, and lay loade at Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes, one would thinke (I woſſe) that there were ſome matter in them: For in oppoſing the Reall preſence, Purgatory, Images, Prayers to Saints, Rayling at the Pope, and the like, you would thinke them to be ſome iollie fellowes, but alas, turne the offenciue weapon towardes him, lay at him a little, and do but teach this bould of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender of others, to defend himſelf, all the behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders burst out in laughter, and the poore ſchollar proues ſo vnskillfull, that the blowes he should re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue vpon his buckler, he beareth them off with his head and shoulders, and is knockt and rapt, euery where, where the Fencer liſtes. For euen ſo Protestantes ſeeme to shew ſome ſmall skill, in offending vs, and our Religion, but being put to defend their owne, alas, what poore Fencers doe they proue? Let the Reader be but an indifferent behoulder of this enſuing combate, and I aſſure him he cannot looke on, but he shall laugh for his labour.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="demands">
                  <div n="1" type="demand">
                     <pb n="131" facs="tcp:23794:66"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 1. <hi>Demaund.</hi> Their first Preachers.</head>
                     <p>VVHETHER the goſpel of Chriſt, was at any time preached in Scotland before Paul Methuen, &amp; ſir Iohn Knox, yea or no?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="demand">
                     <head>2. <hi>VVhence their Doctrine?</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Seing no man ought to preach any doctrine, but that which he hath learned in the Church of God (becauſe as witneſeth <hi>S. Paul</hi>) ſaith cometh by hearing;
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 10</note> I demand from what Doctors or Paſtors Iohn Caluin, ſir Iohn Knox, and their like, firſt learned their new doctrine, now prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in the realme of Scotland?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="demand">
                     <pb n="132" facs="tcp:23794:67"/>
                     <head>3. <hi>VVhence their vocation.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>And ſith it is written, that no man may preach vnles he be ſent;
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 10</note> I dema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d by what power Syr <hi>Iohn Knox,</hi> with other Apoſtataes, Prieſts, Monkes and Friars, tooke vpon them this vocation?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="demand">
                     <head>4. <hi>If Conforme to predeceſſors?</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Seeing you acknowledge in your Confeſſion of faith, that the Sacraments ought only to be mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred, by ſuch as are called ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto by ordinary vocation, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, if your vocation vnto the miniſtrie, be like vnto the calling of all others, who haue gone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you in the Church of Chriſt, ſince the time of the Apoſtles? whom both yee and wee repute and hould to haue been Iawfull paſtors and teachers of his flock,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:23794:67"/>as, S. Cyprian, S. Auguſtin, S. Ambroſe, and diuers others? wishing you to shewin al points, the conformitie of your vocation with that of theirs.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="demand">
                     <head>5. <hi>who their Doctors?</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Seing after the diſcours of the election of your Miniſters, Elders and Deacons, yee acknowledge that the Scriptures make men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a fourth kind of Miniſters leſt vnto the Church of Chriſt, which alſo are very neceſſarie &amp; profitable,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.</note> and are called by the name of teachers and doctors, whoſe office it is to teach and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct the faithfull in ſound do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, prouiding with all dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, that the puritie of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel be not corrupted, ether throgh ignorance or falſe opinion; I pray you to shew, at what time any
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:23794:68"/>Doctors of ſuch calling, haue bene in your Church before Iohn Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin? becauſe the places of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture noted by you, teach and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, that God hath appointed ſuch meanes in his church, that it should neuer be left deſolate, nor yet his Doctrine to decay, for wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Doctors &amp; other teachers.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="demand">
                     <head>6. <hi>Their admiſsion of Tinkers &amp;c.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>And ſeeing yee confes in the ſame place, that men cannot pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit ſo well in the knowledge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſayd, vnles they be firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in the learned tongues, &amp; humane ſciences (for now God doth not commonly worke by miracles) and that therefore it is neceſſary that ſeed be ſowen for the tyme to come, to the end that the Church be not left barren &amp; waſt vnto poſterity: and alſo, that
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:23794:68"/>for this effect ſchooles be erected, wherin youth may be trayned vp in the knowledge, and feare of God; I demand why yee admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at the firſt entry of your do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine into <hi>Scotland,</hi> and yet doe, Taylors, Skinars, and other Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificers, who were neuer inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted but in their owne craft and occupation, which they left and abiured? and out of their owne heades without any further cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling vnto the miniſtery, began to teach the people? hauing for all their learning and forme of prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, ſome English books only, which yet themſelues very hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnderſtood?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="demand">
                     <head>7. <hi>If the only written word be Iudge?</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Seeing that among other heads of your alleadged fayth, this is one principall, that nothing is to
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:23794:69"/>be beleeued,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Cal. l.</hi> 4. <hi>Inſt. c.</hi> 8. <hi>ſect.</hi> 8.</note> but what is found in the written word, I demaund what teſtimony yee haue in the ſame, for aſſurance of your faith in this point? And whether the fayth of the Apoſtles, was grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on the written word or not?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="demand">
                     <head>8. <hi>S. Thomas Ghoſpell.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Where is it written, that there is only foure Ghoſpels? and that the Ghoſpell of S. <hi>Matthew,</hi> with the other three ought to be recea. ued, and not the Ghoſpell of S. <hi>Thomas?</hi> Or what authority hath moued you, to receaue ſom books or chapters for canonical ſcriptur, and to refuſe or reiect others? Or if any man deny any booke of the new Teſtament (as <hi>Martin Luther</hi> doth the epiſtle of S. <hi>Iames</hi>) what argumentes haue yee from the Scripture to condemne him?
<note place="margin">Praef. in nou. Test</note>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="demand">
                     <pb n="137" facs="tcp:23794:69"/>
                     <head>9. <hi>VVhy Iewes credited.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Seeing yee giue ſo great au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to the Synagogue of the Iewes, that according to their canon, yee admit, &amp; reiect ſundry bookes of holy Scripture, why giue yee not the like authority to the Chriſtian church which hath gone before you, in receauing ſuch bookes as are approued by her for canonicall Scripture? And if the only cauſe which moues you to reiect ſuch bookes, be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were not approued by the Synagogue of the Iewes: why by the ſame reaſon reiect yee not Chriſt himſelfe, ſeeing that Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue would not admit him for their Meſſias?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="demand">
                     <head>10. <hi>Churches authoritie.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>If it be the office of the church,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:23794:70"/>to diſcerne betwixt canonicall Scripture and not canoniall as
<note n="a" place="margin">De capt. Bab</note> Luther
<note n="b" place="margin">In prologo cont. Pet. à Soto.</note> Brentius, and other of your owne maſters doe confes; why should not the ſame church be heard of you, in giuing her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation vpon any doubtfull place therof, called in queſtion? Or why call yee more in dout the interpretation of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture giuen by the Church, then the very bookes themſelues? Or why prefer yee, the priuat opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Iohn <hi>Caluin</hi> and your ſelues, before the vniuerſall, and vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme conſent of all Chriſtian people before you?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="demand">
                     <head>11. <hi>Citing only the written word.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Why eſteeme yee,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Calu. l.</hi> 4 <hi>Inſt. c.</hi> 8. <hi>num.</hi> 13.</note> that yee haue an infallible marke of the true religion, becauſe yee cite only the written word, ſeeing
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:23794:70"/>this hath beene common to all heretiques from the beginning? Or what haue you more to ſay for your felues, then they had for themſelues in this point?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="12" type="demand">
                     <head>12. <hi>If Scripture be eaſy?</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>If the Scripture be ſo eaſy as yee teach it to be
<note n="c" place="margin">Luth de ſer. arbit.</note> what hath moued your owne writers, to make ſo many co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mentaryes ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon? Or what is the cauſe that ther is ſo great controuerſy in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as we ſee at this day? Yea, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon the expreſſe wordes of the laſt Teſtament of our Lord? which according to the nature of a Teſtament, should be moſt cleere.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="13" type="demand">
                     <head>13. <hi>Conference of places.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>If the priuate iudgment of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, one conferring Scripture with
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:23794:71"/>Scripture, be a certaine and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible rule of right interpretatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as yee ſay: how is it, that ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny groſſe contradictions are fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in your writinges, gayn-ſaying, not only one another, but your ſelues alſo, as is euident in your owne bookes?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="14" type="demand">
                     <head>14. <hi>No meanes to be reſolued.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Seeing that the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> the Zuinglians and the Caluiniſts, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides an infinite number of other ſectes, doe euery one alleage the written word, for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmation of their contrarie opinions: how shall it be knowen to any man, that would reſolue himſelfe in matters of religion, which of them haue the true word? ſith it is the true vnderſtanding that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the word, and not the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſounding of the voice, as
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:23794:71"/>Chriſt himſelfe ſaith; who ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected to the Saduces,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.</note> that they miſtooke the Scriptures, becauſe they vnderſtood not the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of them?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="15" type="demand">
                     <head>15. <hi>Traditions.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Why deny yee, any credit to be giuen to Traditions, contrary to
<note n="a" place="margin">
                           <hi>Cal. l.</hi> 4. <hi>iuſt. c.</hi> 10.</note> the expres commandment of the Apoſtle, writing to the Theſſalonians in this maner
<note n="b" place="margin">2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.</note> Stand and keepe the Traditions which yee haue receiued, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by word, or by our epiſtle? And alſo contrary to the doctrne of all the auncient doctors of the church? Or how haue yee the Scripture it ſelfe, but by Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? And ſeeing yee will giue no place vnto Traditions, what aſſurance haue yee, that ſince the Natiuitie of Chriſt, there is only
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:23794:72"/>1623. yeares? Or whither it be lawfull for Chriſtian men, to call this point in queſtion, yea or no?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="16" type="demand">
                     <head>16. <hi>Thinges vnwritten, ordered.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>If no Traditions ought to be receiued, shew me where thoſe thinges are written, which S. <hi>Paul</hi> promiſed to ſet in order at his comming to the Corinthians?
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.</note> for if all thinges were contayned in the written word which the Corinthians had receiued, what needed <hi>S. Paul</hi> to promiſe, to putt the reſt in order at his cominge, chiefly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning our Lords ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="16" type="demand">
                     <head>16. <hi>Church not inuiſible.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Seeing Chriſt ſaith. If thy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will not heare thee, tell it vnto the Church, and if he will not heare the Church, let him be
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:23794:72"/>to thee as a heathen &amp; publican: and therfore apoints his Church to be iudge in controuerſies con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning doctrine and maners, how shal a man finde the church: if it be inuiſible? And why affirme yee it ſo to haue bene, ſeeing no recourſe can be had to an inuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble iudge?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="17" type="demand">
                     <head>17. <hi>Their Church how long?</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>How long eſteeme you your Church to haue beene inuiſible? And during the tyme of the inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility therof, if ther were any of your Miniſters that preached the word of God, &amp; adminiſtred the Sacraments in the realm of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land? Alſo who they were that during that time, oppoſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to al hereſies, and confuted them; ſeeing yee acknowledge with vs, ſundrie hereſies to haue
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:23794:73"/>beene euen almoſt in all ages?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="18" type="demand">
                     <head>18. <hi>The Sinagogue viſible.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Seeing Chriſt hath reiected the Sinagogue of the Iewes, &amp; erected and builded to himſelfe a Church of the Gentills,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 28</note> which he hath promiſed to aſiſt and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to the end of the world: how it is poſſible, that the church of Chriſt (againſt his ſaid pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe) hath beene ſo many yeares inuiſible as yee ſuppoſe? Seeing that the aforſayd Synagogue, notwithſtanding the reiection thereof, hath euer beene viſible, and is yet at this preſent in diuers countreyes? ſo that by this your falſe doctrine, yee giue vnto it, euen after the reiection of it, gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ater prerogatiue, then yee vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to giue to the church of Chriſt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="19" type="demand">
                     <pb n="145" facs="tcp:23794:73"/>
                     <head>19. <hi>Tyme of decaying.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Seeing yee confes with your maſter Caluin,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>Inst. c.</hi> 2. <hi>n.</hi> 3.</note> the Romane Church, ſomtime to haue bene the true Church: in what time, &amp; age ſuppoſe yee that it decayed, ſo that the adherents thereof, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of idolatrie could not be ſaued?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="20" type="demand">
                     <head>20 <hi>Suceſſion of theirs.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Seeing God hath giuen ſome Apoſtles, ſome Prophets,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.</note> Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts, and Paſtors, for the gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to gether of the Saints, and for the edification of the body of Chriſt (which is his Church) to the end of the world: I require you (if you be the members of the ſaid body of Chriſt) to shew your Doctors and Paſtors who haue ſucceeded one another ſince the Apoſtles, with continuance of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:23794:74"/>Vniforme doctrine as the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques haue already done?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="21" type="demand">
                     <head>21 <hi>Condemning herefies.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Why rayle yee ſo much againſt the ſeate of Rome, ſeeing by that ſeate, all heretiques haue bene conuicted and condemned?
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>hier. ep.</hi> 17. <hi>ad Dama ſ Aug. cont Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lag.</hi>
                        </note> an euident token that it is of God. And if yee haue the true Curch (as yee alleadge) shew that euer any of yours, haue oppoſed your ſelues againſt any hereſie before our dayes</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="22" type="demand">
                     <head>22 <hi>Imitation of heretiques.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Why follow yee the footſteps of the Donatiſts, who called the chaire of Rome,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Aug. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. lit. Petil. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 51.</note> the chaire of piſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence? Or how could it haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne poſſible, that the ſeat of Rome, could haue withſtood, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nailed againſt all kindes of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſecutions
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:23794:74"/>ſince the begining, and againſt ſo many infidels and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques, if it had bene the chaire of peſtilence, as yee ſay?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="23" type="demand">
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> 23. <hi>Sacraments, ſeales.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>If the Sacraments be only out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward tokens and ſeales (as yee teache) what prerogatiue giue yee to the Sacraments of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Cal. l</hi> 4. <hi>Inſt. c.</hi> 10.1.</note> aboue the Sacraments of the old law?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="24" type="demand">
                     <head>24. <hi>Faith aſſures not grace.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Seeing yee teach, that faith aſſureth you of grace receiued be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the reception of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, how can you ſay, but that they be altogether vnprofitable, and can giue no fur ther confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? For as much as, where aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of grace is already, no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation is required.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="25" type="demand">
                     <pb n="148" facs="tcp:23794:75"/>
                     <head>25. <hi>Value of Sacraments.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Why affirme yee the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to be of no valor, except they be receiued by faith, and not withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding baptiſe infants, who can receiue nothing by faith?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="26" type="demand">
                     <head>26. <hi>Neceſsitie of Baptiſme.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Why abuſe yee the people, teaching that infants without ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſme, obtaine remiſſion of their ſinnes by the faith of their pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, ſith the faith of the parents, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not hinder them to be borne in originall ſinne,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.</note> and to be the ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of wrath, as S. Paul affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="27" type="demand">
                     <head>27. <hi>Preachatiue Baptiſme.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Seeing Baptiſme,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Cal. l.</hi> 4. <hi>Inſt. ca.</hi> 14. <hi>n.</hi> 4.</note> as yee tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, can not conſiſt without prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, and for as much as no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aching
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:23794:75"/>was made at the time yee were baptiſed by the Catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques: what aſſurance haue yee that yee ar yet baptiſed? Or what doth preaching auaile to alitle infant, who wants the vſe of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="28" type="demand">
                     <head>28. <hi>Baptiſme. of Infidels infants.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Why affirme yee with your maſter <hi>Caluin,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">In Antid. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Trid.</note> that the Sacrament of Baptiſme ought only to be mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred to them, who haue alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy obtained the remiſſion of their ſinnes? Seeing therof it followes, moſt euidently, that infants be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten of Infidel parents, should not at all be baptiſed: becauſe they cannot receiue remiſſion of their ſinnes by the faith of their parents, when they are Infidels, or vnfaithfull?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="29" type="demand">
                     <pb n="150" facs="tcp:23794:76"/>
                     <head>29. <hi>Ceremonies of Baptiſme.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Why reiect yee the ceremonies of Baptiſme, which alwayes
<note n="a" place="margin">
                           <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſ. Ar. c.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp;c. Hier.</hi>
                        </note> haue bene vſed in the church of God ſince the dayes of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, name what age ſoeuer you pleaſe? Or how can yee defend your maiſter <hi>Caluin</hi>
                        <note n="b" place="margin">
                           <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>Inſt. c.</hi> 15 <hi>n.</hi> 19.</note> who is not ashamed to affirme, that in the primitiue church, the right &amp; lawfull adminiſtration of Baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, was already corrupted?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="30" type="demand">
                     <head>30. <hi>Confirmation.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Why deny yee the Sacrament of Confirmation? ſeing it is ſo clearly expreſſed in the Acts of the Apoſtles,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Act</hi> 1.19</note> who by the impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of handes, gaue the holy Ghoſt: and alſo confirmed by all ancient writers, yea and as yet retayned by the English Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="31" type="demand">
                     <pb n="151" facs="tcp:23794:76"/>
                     <head>31. <hi>Reall preſence.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>If the body of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, be not really in the B. Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>Inst. c.</hi> 17. <hi>n.</hi> 10. <hi>&amp;</hi> 14</note> why affirme yee with your maſter <hi>Caluin,</hi> that in this Sacrament, by the ſpirit of God, thoſe thinges are conioyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, which are ſeperat: to wit, the body of Chriſt which is in heauen, with vs who are beneath in earth?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="32" type="demand">
                     <head>32. <hi>Receiuing by faith.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Why affirme yee,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Cal. l.</hi> 4. <hi>Inſt. c.</hi> 17. <hi>n.</hi> 10.</note> that we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the body of Chriſt really by faith, if it be not really preſent in the Sacrament; ſeing our faith cannot make that thinge to be, which is not? If therfore his body be not there really, we cannot beleeue that we receiue it really, except we flatly deceiue our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="33" type="demand">
                     <pb n="152" facs="tcp:23794:77"/>
                     <head>33. <hi>lifting vp to heauen.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>In what ſcripture reade yee, that which yee profes with your ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Caluin,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>Inſt. c.</hi> 17. <hi>n.</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> that when yee receiue the ſacrament, Chriſt is made ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely preſent vnto you? Not that he should be on the earth where yee are, but that yee should be lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vp to heauen where he is: and to which of the heauens were the Apoſtles lifted vp, when they had our lord Ieſus Chriſt, ſitting with them in the laſt ſupper?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="34" type="demand">
                     <head>34. <hi>In two places at once.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Why attribut yee more to your owne faith then to the omnipote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t power of God?
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Cal. l.</hi> 4. <hi>Inſt. cap.</hi> 17. <hi>n.</hi> 31.</note> ſaing, that by your faith, yee are truly lifted vp to he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auen (and ſo at one time yee ar both in heauen and earth) and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that Chriſt can cauſe his body
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:23794:77"/>to be really preſent at once in he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auen and earth?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="35" type="demand">
                     <head>35. <hi>Penance.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Why deny yee the ſacrament of Penance,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Cal. l.</hi> 3. <hi>Inst. c.</hi> 4.</note> by the which the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful miniſters of Gods word (as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of his Maieſtie) giue vs remiſſion of our ſinnes, according to the word of Lord Ieſus Chriſt.
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ioh.</hi> 20.</note> Whoſe ſinnes yee forgiue, they are forgiuen, &amp; whoſe yee retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, they are retained?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="36" type="demand">
                     <head>36. <hi>Order.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Why deny yee holy Order to be a ſacrament,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>Inſt. c.</hi> 14. <hi>n.</hi> 20.</note> ſeeing your ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Caluin,</hi> doth moſt euidently confes it to be one: as is moſt manifeſt in the written word of God?
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. <hi>Luc.</hi> 9.</note>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="37" type="demand">
                     <head>37. <hi>Extreame Vnction.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Why deny yee the ſacrament
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:23794:78"/>extreame Vnction, ſeeing the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>S. Iames,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>cap.</hi> 5.</note> ſpeaketh ſo mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly therof, ſaying? Is any ſick among yov? let him ſend for the prieſts of the Church, &amp; let them pray ouer him, and annoint him with oyle in the name of our Lord?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="38" type="demand">
                     <head>38. <hi>Matrimonie.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Why deny yee the ſacrament of mariage,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.</note> ſeeing <hi>S. Paul</hi> witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth in ſo plaine words, that it is a Sacrament? And why doth your maſter <hi>Caluin</hi> lye ſo loudly affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, that no man vntill the time of Gregorie the firſt of that name Pope of Rome,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>In c.</hi> 5. <hi>ad Epheſ l. de fide &amp; op. c.</hi> 7.</note> euer ſaw, that it was giuen for a ſacrament? ſeeing <hi>S. Ambroſe (a) S. August. (b)</hi> and other Doctors (long before <hi>Gregorie</hi>) affirme the ſame in moſt manifeſt wordes to be a ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="39" type="demand">
                     <pb n="155" facs="tcp:23794:78"/>
                     <head>39. <hi>Two wiues at once.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Why permit yee any man to marrie, his firſt wife being yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue? ſeeing <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſaith. That the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which is in ſubiection to a man, her husband being ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue, is bound to the law: but if her husband be dead, she is deliuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the law of her husband? Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if she take another man, whilſt her husband yet liueth, she shall be called an adulteres.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="40" type="demand">
                     <head>40. <hi>Breaking of vowes.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Seeing S. <hi>Paul</hi> affirmes, that thoſe who marrie after they haue made the vow of chaſtity, incur damnation, what hath moued your Apoſtata Prieſts, Monkes, and Friars, to attempt mariage, after their ſo ſolemne vow of chaſtitie, and ſo moſt willfully to
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:23794:79"/>damne themſelues?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="41" type="demand">
                     <head>41. <hi>Sinnes not imputed?</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Why affirme yee, that yee are ſo aſſured that your ſinnes are not imputed to you, as yee are aſſured that God is in heauen, becauſe yee beleeue the one &amp; the other with one faith as yee ſay? And yet not withſtanding, yee beg daylie in our Lords prayer, that your ſinnes may be forgiuen you? which prayer truly were ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous, if this your aſſertion were ſo aſſured.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="42" type="demand">
                     <head>42. <hi>All good workes ſinnes.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Why affirme yee,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Cal. l.</hi> 3. <hi>Inſt. cap.</hi> 14. <hi>n.</hi> 5.11.</note> that all our workes, how good ſoeuer they appeare to be, are nothing but ſinne in the ſight of God, ſith it is impoſſible, that any worke, be good and euill all at once? And
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:23794:79"/>in the Scripture it ſelfe,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.22.3. <hi>Reg.</hi> 10.</note> we reade of ſundry that haue bene comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for their good workes. Or if all our workes be ſinnes, then is it all one, to rob a poore man, and to giue him almes, excepte the one be leſſe ſinne then the other?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="43" type="demand">
                     <head>43. <hi>Falſe aſſurance.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Why affirme yee with your maſter <hi>Caluin,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>Inſt. c.</hi> 2. <hi>n.</hi> 40.</note> that who ſoeuer hath once embraced the light of your goſpell, can neuer perish? conſidering that many who haue bene of your ſect (yea Miniſters themſelues of the higheſt ranck) haue turned to vs, and haue dyed in our Catholique faith: and ſo (according to your doctrine) ar vtterly Damned.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="44" type="demand">
                     <head>44. <hi>Abſurditie by denying a third place.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Seeing on the one ſide, yee
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:23794:80"/>teach that the ſpots of ſinne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne ſo long as we liue:
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Cal. l.</hi> 4. <hi>Inſt. c.</hi> 13 <hi>n.</hi> 10.</note> and on the other ſide deny, both place and time of cleanſing after our death; how can you auoide to declare manifeſtly, that ether none at all enter into heauen, or elſe that they who enter, do ſtill remayne with their ſpots of ſinne a thing ſo expreſly contrary to the word?
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Apoc.</hi> 12.</note>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="45" type="demand">
                     <head>45. <hi>Inuocation of Saints.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Why affirme yee againſt the Scripture, that the Saints in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heare not our prayers, becauſe forſooth that they ar dead? ſeeing Chriſt himſelf ſaith, that God is not the God of the dead,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.</note> but of the liuing? And how can the Saints in heauen reioyce at our repentance if they know not the ſame?
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Luc.</hi> 15.</note>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="46" type="demand">
                     <head>46. <hi>Images.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>If all that haue errected Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:23794:80"/>in the Temple of God be I do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters, how can yee deliuer Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of that ſpot? or yet defend,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Exod.</hi> 25. <hi>&amp;</hi> 37. <hi>Num.</hi> 7.</note> that God himſelfe was not the author of I dolatrie, ſeing he commanded Images to be made for that effect?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="47" type="demand">
                     <head>47. <hi>Renewing old hereſies:</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Why haue yee renewed ſo many old hereſies, condemned ſo many hundred yeares ſince, by the vniuerſall church of God? Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mely, the hereſie of Simon Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus, denying the freewill of man?
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Clem. l.</hi> 2 <hi>Recog.</hi>
                        </note>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="48" type="demand">
                     <head>48. <hi>Of the Pepuſians.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Why haue yee renewed the hereſie of Pepuſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ns, affirming,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Aug. de haer. haer.</hi> 27.</note> that diſtinction of order and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, ought not to be obſerued in the church of God?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="49" type="demand">
                     <head>49. <hi>Of the Nouatians.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Cyp. l.</hi> 4. <hi>ep.</hi> 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note>
                     </head>
                     <p>Why haue yee renewed the
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:23794:81"/>hereſie of the Nouatians denying that all ſinnes are forgiuen by the Sacrament of Penance?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="50" type="demand">
                     <head>50. <hi>Of the Maniches.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Why haue yee renewed the hereſie of the Maniches,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Aug. ad quod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> ult hereſ.</hi> 46.</note> denying the water of Baptiſme, to auayle any thinge to our ſaluation?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="51" type="demand">
                     <head>51. <hi>Of the Donatists.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Why haue yee renewed the here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie of the Donatiſts,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Optat. Mil. l.</hi> 2. <hi>ad Par. de ſciſ. Don.</hi>
                        </note> teaching that the Church of God hath perished thoroughout the whole world, except in ſome obſcure corners? As alſo,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Aug. l.</hi> 2. <hi>cont Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til. c.</hi> 34.</note> that <hi>S. Iohns Baptiſme,</hi> was not different from the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme of our Lord?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="52" type="demand">
                     <head>52. <hi>Of the Arrians.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Why haue yee renewed the hereſies of Arius,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Aug. de hereſ. ad quod vult. Deum hereſ</hi> 13.</note> teaching that it
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:23794:81"/>is not lawfull to offer ſacrifice for the dead? And that there is no difference betweene a Bishop and a ſimple prieſt? nor that the faſting dayes of the Chruch, ought to be kept, but that euery man may faſt, according to his owne will and pleaſure?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="53" type="demand">
                     <head>53. <hi>Of the Eunomians.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Why haue yee renewed the here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie of the Eunomians,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Aug. ad quod wlt Deum hereſ.</hi> 54.</note> that by faith only, man may obtaine life euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="54" type="demand">
                     <head>54. <hi>Of the Pelagians</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Why haue yee renewed the hereſie of the Pelagians,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Aug. ad quod vult hereſ.</hi> 11.</note> teaching that infa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts may be ſaued without Baptiſme?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="55" type="demand">
                     <head>55. <hi>Of the Iouinians.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Why haue yee renewed the
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:23794:82"/>hereſies of <hi>Iouinianus,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Aug. ad quod vult haer</hi> 81.</note> teaching ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage to be as acceptable to God, as virginitie: &amp; that it is lawfull for Monkes &amp; Nunnes to marrie?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="56" type="demand">
                     <head>56. <hi>Of the Vigilantians.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Why haue yee renewed the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies of <hi>Vigilantius,</hi> denying the inuocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Saints, &amp; the hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the relicks of the Martyrs?
<note place="margin">Hier. con Vigil.</note>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="57" type="demand">
                     <head>57. <hi>Of the Eustichians.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Why haue yee renewed the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie of the <hi>Eustachians</hi> affirming that it is not lawful to go in Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage, vnto holy places?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="58" type="demand">
                     <head>58. <hi>Of the Iconomachians.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Why haue yee renewed the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie of the <hi>Iconomachians,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Concil. Gang.</note> breaking downe the Images of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; of his Saints?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="59" type="demand">
                     <head>59. <hi>Of the Beringarians.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Why haue yee renewed the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, of Beringarius, denying the body and blood of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, to be reallie preſent in the
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:23794:82"/>Sacrament of the Altar?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="60" type="demand">
                     <head>60. <hi>Of many other hereſies.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Why haue yee reneued ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>y other hereſies of the Albigenſes, Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſes, Wickliffits, Huſſits, of Abailhardus, of Almaricus, &amp; of other more deteſtable heretiques condemned many years ſince by the church of God?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="61" type="demand">
                     <head>61. <hi>Following heretiques only in ſome pointes.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Why haue yee followed the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forſaid heretiks in theſe pointso<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly in which they haue diſſented fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the whole church of God, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected the reſt of their doctrine?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="62" type="demand">
                     <head>62. <hi>Scottish Reformation.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Whether your Reformation, which yee haue made in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme of Scatland, in pulling downe of the Churches, be not rather like to the Reformatign of Turkes and Pagans, then to a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation made by Chriſtians?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="63" type="demand">
                     <pb n="164" facs="tcp:23794:83"/>
                     <head>63. <hi>Churches made Stables.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Whither in making Stables of the Churches in Scotland (ſo that horſes were ſtabled on your Kinges graues) and in diging vp the bones of Chriſtian men, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble yee rather to be Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, or Infidels and Pagans?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="64" type="demand">
                     <head>64. <hi>Burning Reliques.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>What moued you to burne the holy Reliques of Saints, who were Temples and Tabernacles of the holy Ghoſt, when they liued: which among all Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſince the Apoſtles dayes vnto this preſent, haue bene holden in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor and veneration?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="65" type="demand">
                     <head>65. <hi>Burning the Doct. writinges.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Why burnt yee the writinges of the Doctors &amp; holy fathers, as
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:23794:83"/>of <hi>S. Ambroſe, S. Auguſtine, S. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> and others: and yet shame not to ſay, that yee profeſſe one faith with them?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="66" type="demand">
                     <head>66. <hi>Depoſsing magistrates.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Where is the veritie and effect of your ſolemne proteſtations, promiſing that your Reformatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was not to diſpoſſes any magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrat: when yee haue not only rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vproares in the contrie, and expelled thence the chiefe magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, but in your preachinges, would plainly thrall all kinges, and kingdomes, and haue them ſubiect to the election and puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the people, ſetting forth your ſundry bookes therupon?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="67" type="demand">
                     <head>67. <hi>Libertie of Conſcience.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Why in the begining of your new goſpell, preached yee liberty
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:23794:84"/>of conſcience; &amp; now conſtraine all men to ſubſcribe to your new doctrine: yee them whome yee know to beleeue the contrarie?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="68" type="demand">
                     <head>68. <hi>Profeſsion of pouertie.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Why preached yee, when yee firſt vſurped authoritie to prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, that the Miniſters of the word, ought to profes and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue pouertie as the Apoſtles did: and preſently none in the whole realme are ſo couetous as yee are, not only to giue mony vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> land, but alſo vpon planie vſurie?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="69" type="demand">
                     <head>69. <hi>Churches patrimonie.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Why pretend yee to haue the benefices and patrimonie of the Church, ſeeing yee cannot ſhew your ſelues to be lawfull heires and ſucceſſours to them, who were the true and right poſeſſors
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:23794:84"/>therof before you? And why haue yee reiected as Idolatrie, all that which appertayneth to them whom yee cal papiſtes, excepting only the patrimonie &amp; liuing of the Church? Or if there were no Churchin the contry before your coming, why pretend yee as pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony, any other thing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath already bene giuen to your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation by thoſe of your owne coate?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="70" type="demand">
                     <head>70. <hi>Building Churches.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Seeing one ſpirit could not moue ſo many of our Kinges to build ſo many Churches, Coll<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edges &amp; Abbies, and you to deſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roy the ſame: which of you two may be iuſtly eſteemed, to be moued by the good ſpirit, and which by the euil?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="71" type="demand">
                     <pb n="168" facs="tcp:23794:85"/>
                     <head>71.</head>
                     <p>Finally, whether theſe your doinges, tend not to the abolition of all memorie of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, yea or no? Seing already ſome of you doe dout, in what time of the yeare he was borne, as whether in winter, or in ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer: ſo that apparently, your next dout will be, whether, he was borne or not; which appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res to be the end and concluſion of your new goſpell.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="table_of_contents">
                  <pb facs="tcp:23794:85"/>
                  <head>THE TITLES OF THE DEMANDES Contayned in this booke of D. BRISTOVV,</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 COLLATIO <hi>Carthagine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis pag.</hi> 6</item>
                     <item>2 <hi>Building of the Church</hi> 11</item>
                     <item>3 <hi>Going out</hi> 16</item>
                     <item>4 <hi>After-riſing</hi> 18</item>
                     <item>5 <hi>VVondred at</hi> 20</item>
                     <item>6 <hi>Name of Catholikes</hi> 22</item>
                     <item>7 <hi>Name of Heretikes</hi> 26</item>
                     <item>8 <hi>Name of Proteſtants</hi> 27</item>
                     <item>9 <hi>Conuerſion of Heathen Nationss</hi> 31</item>
                     <item>10 <hi>Miracles</hi> 34</item>
                     <item>11 <hi>England</hi> 38</item>
                     <item>12 <hi>Viſions</hi> 41</item>
                     <item>13 <hi>Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>or of Croſſes</hi> 42</item>
                     <item>14 <hi>Vertue of Croſſe</hi> 45</item>
                     <item>15 <hi>Honor of Saintes</hi> 46</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:23794:86"/>
                     <item>16 <hi>Vertue of Saints</hi> 47</item>
                     <item>17 <hi>Casting out of Diuells.</hi> 48</item>
                     <item>18 <hi>Destroying of Idolatry</hi> 52</item>
                     <item>19 <hi>Kinges</hi> 54</item>
                     <item>20 <hi>In all perſecutions</hi> 57</item>
                     <item>21 <hi>Churches</hi> 60</item>
                     <item>22 <hi>Seruice</hi> 63</item>
                     <item>23 <hi>Apish imitation</hi> 66</item>
                     <item>24 <hi>Prieſthood</hi> 67</item>
                     <item>25 <hi>Monkes</hi> 72</item>
                     <item>26 <hi>Fathers</hi> 73</item>
                     <item>27 <hi>Councells</hi> 75</item>
                     <item>28 <hi>Sea Apoſtolicke</hi> 77</item>
                     <item>29 <hi>Traditions Apoſtolike</hi> 78</item>
                     <item>30 <hi>Their owne Doctors</hi> 79</item>
                     <item>31 <hi>Vniuerſality</hi> 80</item>
                     <item>32 <hi>Antiquity</hi> 82</item>
                     <item>33 <hi>Conſent</hi> 83</item>
                     <item>34 <hi>Authority</hi> 84</item>
                     <item>35 <hi>Vnity</hi> 89</item>
                     <item>36 <hi>Keepers of the Scriptures</hi> 91</item>
                     <item>37 <hi>Store-houſe of all Truth</hi> 92</item>
                     <item>38 <hi>Old Hereſyes</hi> 95</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:23794:86"/>
                     <item>39 <hi>Where grew their dostrine</hi> 96</item>
                     <item>40 <hi>They neuer afore now</hi> 98</item>
                     <item>41 <hi>Studying of all Truth</hi> 99</item>
                     <item>42 <hi>Vnſent</hi> 101</item>
                     <item>43 <hi>Succeſsion</hi> 102</item>
                     <item>44 <hi>Apoſtolike Church</hi> 103</item>
                     <item>45 <hi>Changing</hi> 105</item>
                     <item>46 <hi>Our Auncestors ſaued</hi> 108</item>
                     <item>47 <hi>Communion of Saints</hi> 109</item>
                     <item>48 <hi>VVhere Chriſt worketh</hi> 112</item>
                     <item>49 <hi>All enemyes</hi> 118</item>
                     <item>50 <hi>Sure to continue</hi> 119</item>
                     <item>51 <hi>Apostacy</hi> 119</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="table_of_contents">
                  <head>THE TITLES OF THE DEMANDES Contayned in this other booke.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 <hi>PReachers</hi> 131</item>
                     <item>2 <hi>VVhence their doctrin</hi> 131</item>
                     <item>3 <hi>VVhence their vocation</hi> 132</item>
                     <item>4 <hi>If conforme to predeceſſors?</hi> 132</item>
                     <item>5 <hi>VVho their Doctours?</hi> 133</item>
                     <item>6 <hi>Their admiſsion of Tinkers</hi> 134</item>
                     <item>7 <hi>If the o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> word be Iudg?</hi> 135</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:23794:87"/>
                     <item>8. <hi>S. Thomas Ghoſpell.</hi> 136</item>
                     <item>9. <hi>VVhy Iewes credited.</hi> 137</item>
                     <item>10. <hi>Churches authoritie.</hi> 137</item>
                     <item>11. <hi>Citing only the writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> word.</hi> 138</item>
                     <item>12. <hi>If Scripture be eaſy?</hi> 139</item>
                     <item>13. <hi>Conference of places.</hi> 139</item>
                     <item>14. <hi>No meanes to be reſolued.</hi> 140</item>
                     <item>15. <hi>Traditions.</hi> 141</item>
                     <item>16. <hi>Thinges vnwritten, ordered.</hi> 142</item>
                     <item>16. <hi>Church not inuiſible.</hi> 142</item>
                     <item>17. <hi>Their Church how long?</hi> 143</item>
                     <item>18. <hi>The Sinagogue viſible.</hi> 144</item>
                     <item>19. <hi>Time of decaying.</hi> 145</item>
                     <item>20. <hi>Suceſsion of theirs.</hi> 145</item>
                     <item>21. <hi>Condemning hereſies.</hi> 146</item>
                     <item>22. <hi>Imitation of heretiques.</hi> 146</item>
                     <item>23. <hi>Sacraments, ſeales.</hi> 147</item>
                     <item>24. <hi>Faith aſſures not grace.</hi> 147</item>
                     <item>25. <hi>Value of Sacraments.</hi> 148</item>
                     <item>26. <hi>Neceſsitie of Baptiſme.</hi> 148</item>
                     <item>27. <hi>Preachetiue Baptiſme.</hi> 148</item>
                     <item>28. <hi>Baptiſme of Infidels infants.</hi> 149</item>
                     <item>29. <hi>Ceremonies of Baptiſme,</hi> 150</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:23794:87"/>
                     <item>30. <hi>Confirmation.</hi> 150</item>
                     <item>31. <hi>Reall preſence.</hi> 151</item>
                     <item>32. <hi>Receauing by faith.</hi> 151</item>
                     <item>33. <hi>Lifting vp to heauen.</hi> 152</item>
                     <item>34. <hi>In two places at once.</hi> 152</item>
                     <item>35. <hi>Penance.</hi> 153</item>
                     <item>36. <hi>Order.</hi> 153</item>
                     <item>37. <hi>Extreame vnction.</hi> 153</item>
                     <item>38. <hi>Matrimonie.</hi> 154</item>
                     <item>39. <hi>Two wiues at once.</hi> 155</item>
                     <item>40. <hi>Breaking of Vowes.</hi> 155</item>
                     <item>41. <hi>Sinnes not imputed.</hi> 156</item>
                     <item>42. <hi>All good workes ſinns.</hi> 156</item>
                     <item>43. <hi>Falſe aſſurance.</hi> 157</item>
                     <item>44. <hi>Abſurditie by denying a third place.</hi> 157</item>
                     <item>45. <hi>Inuocation of Saints.</hi> 158</item>
                     <item>46. <hi>Images.</hi> 158</item>
                     <item>47. <hi>Renewing old hereſies.</hi> 159</item>
                     <item>48. <hi>Of the Pepuſians.</hi> 159</item>
                     <item>49. <hi>Of the Nouatians.</hi> 159</item>
                     <item>50. <hi>Of the Maniches.</hi> 160</item>
                     <item>51. <hi>Of the Donatiſts.</hi> 160</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:23794:88"/>
                     <item>52 <hi>Of the Arrians</hi> 160</item>
                     <item>53 <hi>Of the Eunomians</hi> 161</item>
                     <item>54 <hi>Of the Pelagians</hi> 161</item>
                     <item>55 <hi>Of the Iouinians</hi> 161</item>
                     <item>56 <hi>Of the Vigilantians</hi> 162</item>
                     <item>57 <hi>Of the Eustacheans</hi> 162</item>
                     <item>58 <hi>Of the Iconomachians</hi> 162</item>
                     <item>59 <hi>Of the Beringarians</hi> 162</item>
                     <item>60 <hi>Of many other Hereſies</hi> 163</item>
                     <item>61 <hi>Following heretikes only in ſome points</hi> 163</item>
                     <item>62 <hi>Scottish Reformation</hi> 163</item>
                     <item>63 <hi>Churches made Stables</hi> 164</item>
                     <item>64 <hi>Burning reliques</hi> 164</item>
                     <item>65 <hi>Burning the Doct. writings</hi> 164</item>
                     <item>66 <hi>Depoſing Magistrates</hi> 165</item>
                     <item>67 <hi>Liberty of conſcience</hi> 165</item>
                     <item>68 <hi>Profeſsion of Pouerty</hi> 166</item>
                     <item>69 <hi>Churches patrimony</hi> 166</item>
                     <item>70 <hi>Building Churches</hi> 167</item>
                     <item>71 <hi>Aboliſsion of al memory of Chriſt</hi> 168</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="succession_of_popes">
                  <pb facs="tcp:23794:88"/>
                  <p>THE CONTINVAL SVC<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of the Popes of Rome, as it is recorded in all Cronicles &amp; Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtories (beſides many other good writers) both olde and new, wherof I ſay with S, Auguſtine <hi>con. Epiſt. Manichaei, cap.</hi> 4. <hi>In Catholicae Eccleſiae gremio iuſtiſſime tenet me, &amp;c.</hi> Beſides ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other thinges, this moſte wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thely keepeth me in the lappe of the Catholike Church: to wit, the Succeſſion of Prieſtes from S. Peter the Apoſtle him ſelfe (to whom our Lord after his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection <hi>Ioan.</hi> 12. committed the feeding of his sheepe) euen to the Bishop that now is.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23794:89"/>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>The year of our lord.</hi> 33.34</cell>
                           <cell>1</cell>
                           <cell>PETER) 1. <hi>Pet</hi> 5. <hi>ver.</hi> 13.) &amp; Paul. (<hi>Act.</hi> 28) Apoſtles,</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>57</cell>
                           <cell>2</cell>
                           <cell>Linus</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>68</cell>
                           <cell>3</cell>
                           <cell>Clement</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>77</cell>
                           <cell>4</cell>
                           <cell>Cletus</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>84</cell>
                           <cell>5</cell>
                           <cell>Anacletus</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>96</cell>
                           <cell>6</cell>
                           <cell>Euariſtus</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>109</cell>
                           <cell>7</cell>
                           <cell>Alexander</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>117</cell>
                           <cell>8</cell>
                           <cell>Xiſtus</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>127</cell>
                           <cell>9</cell>
                           <cell>Teleſphorus</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>138</cell>
                           <cell>10</cell>
                           <cell>Hyginus</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>142</cell>
                           <cell>11</cell>
                           <cell>Pius</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>153</cell>
                           <cell>12</cell>
                           <cell>Anicetus</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>163</cell>
                           <cell>13</cell>
                           <cell>Soter</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>171</cell>
                           <cell>14</cell>
                           <cell>Eleutherius</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>So farre S. Irenee li.</hi> 3. <hi>ca.</hi> 3. <hi>againſt the Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies of his time.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>186</cell>
                           <cell>15</cell>
                           <cell>Victor</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>198</cell>
                           <cell>16</cell>
                           <cell>Zepherinus</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>218</cell>
                           <cell>17</cell>
                           <cell>Caliſtus</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>223</cell>
                           <cell>18</cell>
                           <cell>Vrbanus</cell>
                        </row>
                        <pb facs="tcp:23794:89"/>
                        <row>
                           <cell>231</cell>
                           <cell>19</cell>
                           <cell>Pontianus</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>236</cell>
                           <cell>20</cell>
                           <cell>Anterus</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>237</cell>
                           <cell>21</cell>
                           <cell>Fabianus</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>251</cell>
                           <cell>22</cell>
                           <cell>Cornelius</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>253</cell>
                           <cell>23</cell>
                           <cell>Lucius</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>255</cell>
                           <cell>24</cell>
                           <cell>Steuen</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>257</cell>
                           <cell>25</cell>
                           <cell>Xiſtus ii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>260</cell>
                           <cell>26</cell>
                           <cell>Dionyſius</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>271</cell>
                           <cell>27</cell>
                           <cell>Felix</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>275</cell>
                           <cell>28</cell>
                           <cell>Eutychianus</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>283</cell>
                           <cell>29</cell>
                           <cell>Caius</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>296</cell>
                           <cell>30</cell>
                           <cell>Marcellinus</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>304</cell>
                           <cell>31</cell>
                           <cell>Marcellus</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>310</cell>
                           <cell>32</cell>
                           <cell>Euſebius</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>311</cell>
                           <cell>33</cell>
                           <cell>Miltiades</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>So farre, all were Martyrs</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>314</cell>
                           <cell>34</cell>
                           <cell>Silueſter</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>336</cell>
                           <cell>35</cell>
                           <cell>Marcus</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>36</cell>
                           <cell>Iulius</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>353</cell>
                           <cell>37</cell>
                           <cell>Liberius</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>366</cell>
                           <cell>38</cell>
                           <cell>Damaſus</cell>
                        </row>
                        <pb facs="tcp:23794:90"/>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>So farre S. Optatus lib.</hi> 2. <hi>againſt the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natistes of his time</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>384</cell>
                           <cell>39</cell>
                           <cell>Siricius</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>398</cell>
                           <cell>40</cell>
                           <cell>Anaſtaſius</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>So farre S. Auguſtin Epiſt.</hi> 165. <hi>againſt the Donatistes of his time</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>401</cell>
                           <cell>41</cell>
                           <cell>Innocentius</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>416</cell>
                           <cell>42</cell>
                           <cell>Zozimus</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>419</cell>
                           <cell>43</cell>
                           <cell>Bonifacius</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>423</cell>
                           <cell>44</cell>
                           <cell>Caeleſtinus</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>432</cell>
                           <cell>45</cell>
                           <cell>Xiſtus iii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>440</cell>
                           <cell>46</cell>
                           <cell>Leo the Great</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>461</cell>
                           <cell>47</cell>
                           <cell>Hilarius</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>467</cell>
                           <cell>48</cell>
                           <cell>Simplicius</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>483</cell>
                           <cell>49</cell>
                           <cell>Felix ii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>492</cell>
                           <cell>50</cell>
                           <cell>Gelaſius</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>496</cell>
                           <cell>51</cell>
                           <cell>Anaſtaſius ii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>498</cell>
                           <cell>52</cell>
                           <cell>Symmachus.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>514</cell>
                           <cell>53</cell>
                           <cell>Hormisda</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>523</cell>
                           <cell>54</cell>
                           <cell>Ihon</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>526</cell>
                           <cell>55</cell>
                           <cell>Felix iii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <pb facs="tcp:23794:90"/>
                        <row>
                           <cell>530</cell>
                           <cell>56</cell>
                           <cell>Bonifacius ii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>532</cell>
                           <cell>57</cell>
                           <cell>Iohn ii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>534</cell>
                           <cell>58</cell>
                           <cell>Agapetus</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>535</cell>
                           <cell>59</cell>
                           <cell>Siluerius</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>537</cell>
                           <cell>60</cell>
                           <cell>P Vigilius</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>556</cell>
                           <cell>61</cell>
                           <cell>Pelagius</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>561</cell>
                           <cell>62</cell>
                           <cell>Iohn iii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>575</cell>
                           <cell>63</cell>
                           <cell>Benedict</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>579</cell>
                           <cell>64</cell>
                           <cell>Pelagius ii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>590</cell>
                           <cell>65</cell>
                           <cell>Gregory the Great</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>604</cell>
                           <cell>66</cell>
                           <cell>Sabinianus</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>605</cell>
                           <cell>67</cell>
                           <cell>Bonifacius iii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>606</cell>
                           <cell>68</cell>
                           <cell>Bonifacius iiii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>613</cell>
                           <cell>69</cell>
                           <cell>Deusdedit</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>617</cell>
                           <cell>70</cell>
                           <cell>Bonifacius v</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>So farre, all Saintes but one, as many alſo in them that folow.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>627</cell>
                           <cell>71</cell>
                           <cell>Honorius</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>638</cell>
                           <cell>72</cell>
                           <cell>Seuerinus</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>638</cell>
                           <cell>73</cell>
                           <cell>S. Iohn iiii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>640</cell>
                           <cell>74</cell>
                           <cell>S. Theodore</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>647</cell>
                           <cell>75</cell>
                           <cell>S. Martin i</cell>
                        </row>
                        <pb facs="tcp:23794:91"/>
                        <row>
                           <cell>654</cell>
                           <cell>76</cell>
                           <cell>Eugenius</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>657</cell>
                           <cell>77</cell>
                           <cell>Vitalianus</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>672</cell>
                           <cell>78</cell>
                           <cell>S. Adeodatus</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>976</cell>
                           <cell>79</cell>
                           <cell>Domnus</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>679</cell>
                           <cell>80</cell>
                           <cell>Agatho</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>682</cell>
                           <cell>81</cell>
                           <cell>S. Leo ii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>684</cell>
                           <cell>82</cell>
                           <cell>S. Benedict ii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>685</cell>
                           <cell>83</cell>
                           <cell>Iohn v</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>686</cell>
                           <cell>84</cell>
                           <cell>Cuno</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>687</cell>
                           <cell>85</cell>
                           <cell>S. Sergius</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>701</cell>
                           <cell>86</cell>
                           <cell>Iohn vi</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>705</cell>
                           <cell>87</cell>
                           <cell>Iohn vii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>707</cell>
                           <cell>88</cell>
                           <cell>Siſinnius</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>708</cell>
                           <cell>89</cell>
                           <cell>Conſtantinus</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>716</cell>
                           <cell>90</cell>
                           <cell>Gregorie ii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>731</cell>
                           <cell>91</cell>
                           <cell>Gregory iii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>741</cell>
                           <cell>92</cell>
                           <cell>Zachary</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>752</cell>
                           <cell>93</cell>
                           <cell>Steuen ii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>94</cell>
                           <cell>Steuen iii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>757</cell>
                           <cell>95</cell>
                           <cell>Paul</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>768</cell>
                           <cell>96</cell>
                           <cell>Steuen iiii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>772</cell>
                           <cell>97</cell>
                           <cell>Hadrian</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>796</cell>
                           <cell>98</cell>
                           <cell>Leo iii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <pb facs="tcp:23794:91"/>
                        <row>
                           <cell>816</cell>
                           <cell>99</cell>
                           <cell>Steuen v</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>817</cell>
                           <cell>100</cell>
                           <cell>Paſchalis</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>824</cell>
                           <cell>101</cell>
                           <cell>Eugenius ii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>827</cell>
                           <cell>102</cell>
                           <cell>Valentine</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>828</cell>
                           <cell>103</cell>
                           <cell>Gregory iiii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>844</cell>
                           <cell>104</cell>
                           <cell>Sergius ii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>847</cell>
                           <cell>105</cell>
                           <cell>Leo iiii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>855</cell>
                           <cell>106</cell>
                           <cell>Benedict iii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>858</cell>
                           <cell>107</cell>
                           <cell>Nicolas</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>867</cell>
                           <cell>108</cell>
                           <cell>Hadrian ii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>872</cell>
                           <cell>109</cell>
                           <cell>Iohn viii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>882</cell>
                           <cell>110</cell>
                           <cell>Marinus ii.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>884</cell>
                           <cell>111</cell>
                           <cell>Hadrian iii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>885</cell>
                           <cell>112</cell>
                           <cell>Steuen vi</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>891</cell>
                           <cell>113</cell>
                           <cell>Formoſus</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>895</cell>
                           <cell>114</cell>
                           <cell>Bonifacius vi</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>896</cell>
                           <cell>115</cell>
                           <cell>Steuen vii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>897</cell>
                           <cell>116</cell>
                           <cell>Romane</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>117</cell>
                           <cell>Theodore ii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>118</cell>
                           <cell>Iohn ix</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>899</cell>
                           <cell>119</cell>
                           <cell>Benedict iiii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>903</cell>
                           <cell>120</cell>
                           <cell>Leo v</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>121</cell>
                           <cell>Chriſtophor</cell>
                        </row>
                        <pb facs="tcp:23794:92"/>
                        <row>
                           <cell>904</cell>
                           <cell>122</cell>
                           <cell>Sergius iii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>911</cell>
                           <cell>123</cell>
                           <cell>Anaſtaſius iii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>913</cell>
                           <cell>124</cell>
                           <cell>Lando</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>914</cell>
                           <cell>125</cell>
                           <cell>Iohn x</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>628</cell>
                           <cell>126</cell>
                           <cell>Leo vi</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>127</cell>
                           <cell>Steuen viii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>930</cell>
                           <cell>128</cell>
                           <cell>Iohn xi</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>935</cell>
                           <cell>129</cell>
                           <cell>Leo vii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>959</cell>
                           <cell>130</cell>
                           <cell>Steuen ix</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>942</cell>
                           <cell>131</cell>
                           <cell>Marinus iii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>946</cell>
                           <cell>132</cell>
                           <cell>Agapetus ii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>956</cell>
                           <cell>133</cell>
                           <cell>Iohn xii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>963</cell>
                           <cell>134</cell>
                           <cell>Leo viii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>965</cell>
                           <cell>135</cell>
                           <cell>Iohn xiii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>972</cell>
                           <cell>136</cell>
                           <cell>Domnus ii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>137</cell>
                           <cell>Benedict v</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>972</cell>
                           <cell>138</cell>
                           <cell>Bonefacius vii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>975</cell>
                           <cell>139</cell>
                           <cell>Benedict vi</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>984</cell>
                           <cell>140</cell>
                           <cell>Iohn xiiii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>985</cell>
                           <cell>141</cell>
                           <cell>Iohn xv</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>995</cell>
                           <cell>142</cell>
                           <cell>Iohn xvi</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>143</cell>
                           <cell>Gregorie v</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>998</cell>
                           <cell>144</cell>
                           <cell>Silueſter ii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <pb facs="tcp:23794:92"/>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1003</cell>
                           <cell>145</cell>
                           <cell>Iohn xvii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>146</cell>
                           <cell>Iohn xviii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1009</cell>
                           <cell>147</cell>
                           <cell>Sergius iiii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1012</cell>
                           <cell>148</cell>
                           <cell>Benedict vii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1024</cell>
                           <cell>149</cell>
                           <cell>Iohn xix</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1032</cell>
                           <cell>150</cell>
                           <cell>Benedict viii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1045</cell>
                           <cell>151</cell>
                           <cell>Gregorie vi</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1047</cell>
                           <cell>152</cell>
                           <cell>Clement ii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1048</cell>
                           <cell>153</cell>
                           <cell>Damaſus ii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1049</cell>
                           <cell>154</cell>
                           <cell>Leo ix</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1055</cell>
                           <cell>155</cell>
                           <cell>Victor ii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1057</cell>
                           <cell>156</cell>
                           <cell>Steuen ix</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1059</cell>
                           <cell>157</cell>
                           <cell>Nicolas ii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1061</cell>
                           <cell>158</cell>
                           <cell>Alexander ii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1073</cell>
                           <cell>159</cell>
                           <cell>Gregorie vii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1086</cell>
                           <cell>160</cell>
                           <cell>Victor iii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1088</cell>
                           <cell>161</cell>
                           <cell>Vrbanus ii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1099</cell>
                           <cell>162</cell>
                           <cell>Paſchalis ii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1118</cell>
                           <cell>163</cell>
                           <cell>Gelaſius ii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1119</cell>
                           <cell>164</cell>
                           <cell>Calliſtus ii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1124</cell>
                           <cell>165</cell>
                           <cell>Honorius ii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1130</cell>
                           <cell>166</cell>
                           <cell>Innocentius ii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1143</cell>
                           <cell>167</cell>
                           <cell>Caeleſtinus ii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <pb facs="tcp:23794:93"/>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1144</cell>
                           <cell>168</cell>
                           <cell>Lucius ii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1145</cell>
                           <cell>169</cell>
                           <cell>Eugenius iii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1153</cell>
                           <cell>170</cell>
                           <cell>Anaſtaſius iiii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1154</cell>
                           <cell>171</cell>
                           <cell>Hadrian iiii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1159</cell>
                           <cell>172</cell>
                           <cell>Alexander iii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1181</cell>
                           <cell>173</cell>
                           <cell>Lucius iii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1185</cell>
                           <cell>174</cell>
                           <cell>Vrbanus iii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1187</cell>
                           <cell>175</cell>
                           <cell>Gregorie viii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1188</cell>
                           <cell>176</cell>
                           <cell>Clement iii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1191</cell>
                           <cell>177</cell>
                           <cell>Caeleſtinus iii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1198</cell>
                           <cell>178</cell>
                           <cell>Innocentius iii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1216</cell>
                           <cell>179</cell>
                           <cell>Honorius iii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1227</cell>
                           <cell>180</cell>
                           <cell>Gregorie ix</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1241</cell>
                           <cell>181</cell>
                           <cell>Caeleſtinus iiii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1243</cell>
                           <cell>182</cell>
                           <cell>Innocentius iiii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1254</cell>
                           <cell>183</cell>
                           <cell>Alexander iiii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1261</cell>
                           <cell>184</cell>
                           <cell>Vrbanus iiii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1265</cell>
                           <cell>185</cell>
                           <cell>Clement iiii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1271</cell>
                           <cell>186</cell>
                           <cell>Gregorie x</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1276</cell>
                           <cell>187</cell>
                           <cell>Innocentius v</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>188</cell>
                           <cell>Hadrian v</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>189</cell>
                           <cell>Iohn xx</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1277</cell>
                           <cell>190</cell>
                           <cell>Nicholas iii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <pb facs="tcp:23794:93"/>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1281</cell>
                           <cell>191</cell>
                           <cell>Martin iiii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1285</cell>
                           <cell>192</cell>
                           <cell>Honorius iiii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1288</cell>
                           <cell>193</cell>
                           <cell>Nicolas iiii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>2294</cell>
                           <cell>194</cell>
                           <cell>Caeleſtinus v</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1295</cell>
                           <cell>195</cell>
                           <cell>Bonifacius viiii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1303</cell>
                           <cell>196</cell>
                           <cell>Benedict ix</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1305</cell>
                           <cell>197</cell>
                           <cell>Clement v</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1316</cell>
                           <cell>198</cell>
                           <cell>Iohn xxi</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1334</cell>
                           <cell>199</cell>
                           <cell>Benedict x</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1342</cell>
                           <cell>200</cell>
                           <cell>Clement vi</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1352</cell>
                           <cell>201</cell>
                           <cell>Innocentius vi</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1362</cell>
                           <cell>202</cell>
                           <cell>Vrbanus v</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1371</cell>
                           <cell>203</cell>
                           <cell>Gregorie xi</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1378</cell>
                           <cell>204</cell>
                           <cell>Vrbanus vi</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1389</cell>
                           <cell>205</cell>
                           <cell>Bonifacius ix</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1404</cell>
                           <cell>206</cell>
                           <cell>Innocentius vii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1406</cell>
                           <cell>207</cell>
                           <cell>Gregorie xii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1409</cell>
                           <cell>208</cell>
                           <cell>Alexander v</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1410</cell>
                           <cell>209</cell>
                           <cell>Iohn xxii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1417</cell>
                           <cell>210</cell>
                           <cell>Martin v</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1431</cell>
                           <cell>211</cell>
                           <cell>Eugenius iiii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1447</cell>
                           <cell>212</cell>
                           <cell>Nicolas v</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1455</cell>
                           <cell>213</cell>
                           <cell>Calliſtus iii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <pb facs="tcp:23794:94"/>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1458</cell>
                           <cell>214</cell>
                           <cell>Pius ii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1464</cell>
                           <cell>215</cell>
                           <cell>Paul ii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1471</cell>
                           <cell>216</cell>
                           <cell>Xiſtus iiii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1484</cell>
                           <cell>217</cell>
                           <cell>Innocentius viii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1492</cell>
                           <cell>218</cell>
                           <cell>Alexander vi</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1503</cell>
                           <cell>219</cell>
                           <cell>Pius iii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>220</cell>
                           <cell>Iulius ii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1513</cell>
                           <cell>221</cell>
                           <cell>Leo x</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1517</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>vnder them Luther riſeth</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1522</cell>
                           <cell>222</cell>
                           <cell>Hadrian vi</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1523</cell>
                           <cell>223</cell>
                           <cell>Clement vii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1534</cell>
                           <cell>224</cell>
                           <cell>Paul iii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1550</cell>
                           <cell>225</cell>
                           <cell>Iulius iii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1555</cell>
                           <cell>226</cell>
                           <cell>Marcellus ii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>227</cell>
                           <cell>Paul iiii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1560</cell>
                           <cell>228</cell>
                           <cell>Pius iiii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1566</cell>
                           <cell>229</cell>
                           <cell>Pius v</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1572</cell>
                           <cell>230</cell>
                           <cell>Gregorie xiii</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23794:94"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>Venite fratres ſi vultis, &amp;c.</hi> Come brethren if ye will, that you may be graffed in the vine, it is a greif to ſee you lie ſo cut of. Nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber the prieſtes euen from the very See of Peter: and in that order of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſe who ſucceded who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. That is the Rocke, which the proude gates of hel do not ouercome. So ſaide <hi>S. Auguſtine,</hi> a branch then cleuing to the vine, in the Pſalme that he made againſt the piece of Donate an Archeheretike of that time. And euen ſo ſay wee that now likewiſe are of the wholle vine, to theſe pieces of Luther &amp; <hi>Caluine</hi> and others, that haue in our time cut off them ſelues. Or els, if we ſay not well, let them al lay their heads together, &amp; shew that which they hitherto could neuer shew: that Gregorie the fiftenth who now is Pope, and
<pb facs="tcp:23794:95"/>from whom it pleaſeth them to diſſent in ſo many Articles of Faith: that either he (I ſay) is, or any other of the Popes, his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors, was, the firſt amongſt the Popes, that brought or tooke into the Romanes faith the ſaide Articles, or any one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Sure it is, that they cannot ſo charge neither this, nor no other Pope. And therefore plaine it is, that the Romans are ſtill in S. Peter &amp; S. Paules faith, as they were whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> S. Paul wrote vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore againe with S. Auguſtine, <hi>Ipſa est Petra,</hi> This is the Rocke which the proud gates of hell do not ouercome.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23794:95"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23794:96"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23794:96"/>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
